<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<!-- This is a WordPress eXtended RSS file generated by WordPress as an export of your site. -->
<!-- It contains information about your site's posts, pages, comments, categories, and other content. -->
<!-- You may use this file to transfer that content from one site to another. -->
<!-- This file is not intended to serve as a complete backup of your site. -->

<!-- To import this information into a WordPress site follow these steps: -->
<!-- 1. Log in to that site as an administrator. -->
<!-- 2. Go to Tools: Import in the WordPress admin panel. -->
<!-- 3. Install the "WordPress" importer from the list. -->
<!-- 4. Activate & Run Importer. -->
<!-- 5. Upload this file using the form provided on that page. -->
<!-- 6. You will first be asked to map the authors in this export file to users -->
<!--    on the site. For each author, you may choose to map to an -->
<!--    existing user on the site or to create a new user. -->
<!-- 7. WordPress will then import each of the posts, pages, comments, categories, etc. -->
<!--    contained in this file into your site. -->


<rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:excerpt="http://wordpress.org/export/1.2/excerpt/"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:wp="http://wordpress.org/export/1.2/"
>

<channel>
	<title>Brevity: A Journal of Concise Literary Nonfiction</title>
	<link>http://brevitymag.com</link>
	<description>Brevity: The journal devoted exclusively to the concise literary nonfiction.</description>
	<pubDate>Fri, 28 Apr 2017 21:01:20 +0000</pubDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<wp:wxr_version>1.2</wp:wxr_version>
	<wp:base_site_url>http://brevitymag.com</wp:base_site_url>
	<wp:base_blog_url>http://brevitymag.com</wp:base_blog_url>

	<wp:author><wp:author_id>3</wp:author_id><wp:author_login><![CDATA[elhajj]]></wp:author_login><wp:author_email><![CDATA[tim.elhajj@gmail.com]]></wp:author_email><wp:author_display_name><![CDATA[Tim Elhajj]]></wp:author_display_name><wp:author_first_name><![CDATA[Tim]]></wp:author_first_name><wp:author_last_name><![CDATA[Elhajj]]></wp:author_last_name></wp:author>

	<wp:category>
		<wp:term_id>207</wp:term_id>
		<wp:category_nicename><![CDATA[issue-29-january-2009]]></wp:category_nicename>
		<wp:category_parent><![CDATA[]]></wp:category_parent>
		<wp:cat_name><![CDATA[Issue 29 / January 2009]]></wp:cat_name>
	</wp:category>

	

	<item>
		<title>The Bluest Eye</title>
		<link>http://brevitymag.com/nonfiction/the-bluest-eye/</link>
		<pubDate>Thu, 15 Jan 2009 18:50:27 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[elhajj]]></dc:creator>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://brevitymag.com/?p=4366</guid>
		<description></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p align="left"><img class="alignright size-full wp-image-4371" src="http://brevitymag.com/wp-content/uploads/2015/09/Isis.jpg" alt="Isis" width="300" height="448" />Without warning, as if following some Biblical injunction, the boy reached in and plucked out his left eye.  He did it quickly, right hand ambushing his face.  My sister and I stepped back.  It’s rare for a glass eye to make it into your home.  And even more rare for it to pop out.  There it lay in his grimy palm, wet with eye goop, scanning my mother’s kitchen for a more responsible owner.  I can’t remember the boy’s name, only that his mother dropped him off while she ran a quickie sewing errand with my mom.  Either he was the son of La Vawn, the beautician, who frosted my mother’s hair each month, or the boy who lived in the subterranean WW II house that waited, like a jilted bride, for a main floor that never showed up.  In a Saturday morning cartoon, this stray eye would have fallen to the floor into a competitive game of marbles only to be chased for twenty chaotic minutes by a pair of squeaky chipmunks.  But Saturday was long past, and that eye had no chance of rolling anywhere.  It was concave, more like half an eye, which made me want it even more.  My sister was more interested in the caved-in eyelid.  “Want to see what it’s like <em>inside</em>?” the boy said.  I was about to stop him, when he pulled back the folds with his free hand.  “Yuck,” my sister said, and I elbowed her.  “Well it is yuck,” she said.  Moist and pink but clean looking.  More mouth than wound.  Then he closed it, and I looked from the blue eye on his face to the bluer one in his hand.  “They make them in a factory,” he said, “all different colors.”  What a field trip that would make, better than a warehouse of polished agates.  I knew the eye in his hand was only glass, but my, how it glinted—like it possessed special powers.  If you rubbed the eye in just the right way and repeated the right spell, then closed your own eyes, maybe the iris would blink into seeing, and relay pictures straight to your brain.  My brain.  The possibilities were endless: send it to the drive-in on Sunday nights when movies were taboo, tape it to a pigeon’s leg and let it spy on the neighbors, drop it into the Blackfoot Reservoir to search out the trophy trout no one could hook, slide it under the door to the girls’ bathroom during recess.  “Can I hold it?” I said.  The boy without a name looked me over, as if he were weighing the seriousness of our half-hour friendship.  Slowly, very slowly, he held out his hand.  Just as I was reaching for the eye, his mother drove up.  He flipped on the faucet, swiped the eye under the water two or three times, then leaned his head back like a teenager putting in a contact.  And the room turned back into a kitchen, and I slapped off the water, and all three of us blinked, and kept blinking, to get that eye back in place before the vigilant mothers entered the house.</p>
<p align="left">---</p>
<p align="left"><strong>Lance Larsen</strong>’s third collection of poetry, <em>Backyard Alchemy,</em> will appear in 2009 from University of Tampa Press. He has published essays in <em>Iowa Review, Black Warrior Review, Quarterly West, Bellingham Review</em>, and <em>Hunger Mountain</em>. He has received a Pushcart Prize and fellowships from Sewanee, the Ragdale Foundation, and the National Endowment for the Arts. A professor of English at BYU, he will co-direct in 2009 a theater study abroad program in London.</p>
<p style="text-align: right;">photo by <a href="http://kristin.fouquet.cc/" target="_blank">Kristin Fouquet</a></p>]]></content:encoded>
		<excerpt:encoded><![CDATA[]]></excerpt:encoded>
		<wp:post_id>4366</wp:post_id>
		<wp:post_date><![CDATA[2009-01-15 13:50:27]]></wp:post_date>
		<wp:post_date_gmt><![CDATA[2009-01-15 18:50:27]]></wp:post_date_gmt>
		<wp:comment_status><![CDATA[open]]></wp:comment_status>
		<wp:ping_status><![CDATA[open]]></wp:ping_status>
		<wp:post_name><![CDATA[the-bluest-eye]]></wp:post_name>
		<wp:status><![CDATA[publish]]></wp:status>
		<wp:post_parent>0</wp:post_parent>
		<wp:menu_order>0</wp:menu_order>
		<wp:post_type><![CDATA[post]]></wp:post_type>
		<wp:post_password><![CDATA[]]></wp:post_password>
		<wp:is_sticky>0</wp:is_sticky>
		<category domain="post_tag" nicename="characterization"><![CDATA[characterization]]></category>
		<category domain="post_tag" nicename="imagery"><![CDATA[imagery]]></category>
		<category domain="category" nicename="introductory-post-for-issues"><![CDATA[Introductory Post for Issues]]></category>
		<category domain="category" nicename="issue-29-january-2009"><![CDATA[Issue 29 / January 2009]]></category>
		<category domain="category" nicename="nonfiction"><![CDATA[Nonfiction]]></category>
		<category domain="post_tag" nicename="seeing"><![CDATA[seeing]]></category>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key><![CDATA[_edit_last]]></wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[2]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key><![CDATA[Author]]></wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[LANCE LARSEN]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
	</item>
	<item>
		<title>Beyond Chagrin</title>
		<link>http://brevitymag.com/nonfiction/beyond-chagrin/</link>
		<pubDate>Tue, 13 Jan 2009 10:54:52 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[elhajj]]></dc:creator>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://brevitymag.com/?p=4457</guid>
		<description></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p align="left"><img class="alignright size-full wp-image-4377" src="http://brevitymag.com/wp-content/uploads/2015/09/Tracks.jpg" alt="Tracks" width="300" height="375" />When I was in the second grade I wet my pants.</p>
<p align="left">At a rehearsal of my grade school’s pageant, just before I spoke my lines—well, <em>line, </em>but, according to the director, a fourth grade teacher who’d minored in drama, it was a crucial one. For in this version of “Little Red Riding Hood” the BIG BAD WOLF (Yours Truly) is transformed from a predator, lurking and growling (Grrr) upstage to a protector who, in the last scene, comes downstage and to Our Heroine’s defense: “Leave her alone! Grrr!”</p>
<p align="left">I’m not sure I grasped that particular symbolism, but I did grasp that all the other speaking parts had been given to sixth graders; also that I was one of the few Negro children in the school. So I studied my line and practiced my growling, the better to be a credit to my race with, my dear.</p>
<p align="left">I had a sixth-grade reading level, but only a second-grade bladder, and the script called for the WOLF to lurk in every scene. I managed in piecemeal rehearsals, but at the end of the first full run-through, as I stepped downstage, I experienced a release of dramatic tension. Despite the deluge I spoke my line, then exited stage left, dripping.</p>
<p align="left">Lurking in the Boys Room, waiting for my mother to fetch fresh pants, I <em>grred</em> furiously, my belly burning with the acid of chagrin. BIG BAD WOLF? Big, bad disgrace—to myself, my Negro schoolmates, the entire Negro race. Next day the director assured me I’d do fine in performance, that delivering my line when no longer under pressure showed stage presence, but kept having flashbacks. Finally just told me, flatly, to get over it, because though now it seemed a huge event, it was probably not the most embarrassing thing I’d ever do.</p>
<p align="left">A terrifying prophecy—and too often fulfilled. In high school, a plethora of peccadilloes, like that chemistry experiment that produced not the predicted white precipitate but a green cloud of poison gas, or that jump-shot at the buzzer that swished through the opponents’ net. In college, in the city, a myriad of misdemeanors arising from my rural, culturally incompetent upbringing.</p>
<p align="left">I did not order a ham sandwich in a kosher deli… but I did order a corned beef with Swiss. I did ask if I could get sashimi well done. I did whisper to a nun, one February Wednesday morning, that she’d an ash smudge on her forehead. I did amuse the few black students in the school with my abject ignorance of What Was Happening, Where It Was At or the Usual Places to buy tickets to It. If I became (or was made) aware that I’d stepped in It, I’d insert the same foot in my mouth in lame attempts at self-justification (Well, where <em>I </em>come from we fry our fish) but later I’d lie sleepless, haunted by the ghosts of <em>faux pas</em>present<em>, </em>past and future.</p>
<p align="left">In later life I learned (the hard way) to check my facts, my pronunciations and my fly—better to be caught at that than to lecture with one’s zipper down. I developed coping strategies: a deadpan affect that encouraged comic interpretations of potential gaffes; a Socratic style that made obtuse questions methodology; ironies instantly deployable if <em>savoir </em>fell behind<em>faire. </em>Still many ironies were unintended (Would your friend Bill like to join us for a drink?) many obtusities unfeigned (I really thought that working girl was a grad student doing fieldwork). And no strategy could cope with the premonition that the worst gaffe yet lay ahead.</p>
<p align="left">But recently, listening to an old friend introduce me to a distinguished academic audience with a much-embellished account (I did <em>not </em>attempt to leap it in a single bound, I was just trying to climb the thing) of one of my Greatest Misses, it occurred to me that I am no longer vulnerable to such embarrassment; these days I couldn’t even lift my leg that high. Then it struck me: at fifty-something, the most embarrassing thing I’ll ever do is probably something I’ve already done. So I checked my fly and I took the stage, in a state of grace beyond disgrace, beyond the fear of future mortification, beyond chagrin.</p>
<p align="left">---</p>
<p align="left"><strong>David Bradley</strong> is the author of two novels, <a href="http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/0844663239?ie=UTF8&amp;tag=brevitynonfic-20&amp;linkCode=as2&amp;camp=1789&amp;creative=390957&amp;creativeASIN=0844663239" target="_blank">South Street</a><img src="http://www.assoc-amazon.com/e/ir?t=brevitynonfic-20&amp;l=as2&amp;o=1&amp;a=0844663239" alt="" width="1" height="1" border="0" /> and <a href="http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/0060916818?ie=UTF8&amp;tag=brevitynonfic-20&amp;linkCode=as2&amp;camp=1789&amp;creative=390957&amp;creativeASIN=0060916818" target="_blank">The Chaneysville Incident</a><img src="http://www.assoc-amazon.com/e/ir?t=brevitynonfic-20&amp;l=as2&amp;o=1&amp;a=0060916818" alt="" width="1" height="1" border="0" />. The latter won the 1982 PEN/Faulkner Award and an Academy Award from the American Academy and Institute of Arts and Letters. He has published articles in <em>Esquire</em>, <em>Redbook</em>, <em>The New Yorker</em>, the <em>New York Times Magazine</em>, the <em>Philadelphia Inquirer</em><em>Magazine</em>, the <em>Los Angeles Times</em>, and <em>The Village Voice</em> and other periodicals. He is currently at work on a nonfiction book, <em>The Bondage Hypothesis: Meditations on Race and History</em> and a novel-in-stories, <em>Raystown</em>.</p>
<p align="right"><span style="font-size: small;">photo by <a href="http://kristin.fouquet.cc/" target="_blank">Kristin Fouquet</a></span></p>]]></content:encoded>
		<excerpt:encoded><![CDATA[]]></excerpt:encoded>
		<wp:post_id>4457</wp:post_id>
		<wp:post_date><![CDATA[2009-01-13 05:54:52]]></wp:post_date>
		<wp:post_date_gmt><![CDATA[2009-01-13 10:54:52]]></wp:post_date_gmt>
		<wp:comment_status><![CDATA[open]]></wp:comment_status>
		<wp:ping_status><![CDATA[open]]></wp:ping_status>
		<wp:post_name><![CDATA[beyond-chagrin]]></wp:post_name>
		<wp:status><![CDATA[publish]]></wp:status>
		<wp:post_parent>0</wp:post_parent>
		<wp:menu_order>0</wp:menu_order>
		<wp:post_type><![CDATA[post]]></wp:post_type>
		<wp:post_password><![CDATA[]]></wp:post_password>
		<wp:is_sticky>0</wp:is_sticky>
		<category domain="post_tag" nicename="characterization"><![CDATA[characterization]]></category>
		<category domain="post_tag" nicename="childhoodfamily"><![CDATA[childhood/family]]></category>
		<category domain="category" nicename="issue-29-january-2009"><![CDATA[Issue 29 / January 2009]]></category>
		<category domain="post_tag" nicename="list"><![CDATA[list]]></category>
		<category domain="category" nicename="nonfiction"><![CDATA[Nonfiction]]></category>
		<category domain="post_tag" nicename="persona"><![CDATA[persona]]></category>
		<category domain="post_tag" nicename="personal_essay"><![CDATA[personal_essay]]></category>
		<category domain="post_tag" nicename="raceethnicity"><![CDATA[race/ethnicity]]></category>
		<category domain="post_tag" nicename="speculation"><![CDATA[speculation]]></category>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key><![CDATA[Author]]></wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[DAVID BRADLEY]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key><![CDATA[_edit_last]]></wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[2]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
	</item>
	<item>
		<title>Jimi Don&#039;t Play Here No More</title>
		<link>http://brevitymag.com/nonfiction/jimi-dont-play-here-no-more/</link>
		<pubDate>Mon, 12 Jan 2009 10:54:49 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[elhajj]]></dc:creator>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://brevitymag.com/?p=4459</guid>
		<description></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p align="left"><img class="alignright size-full wp-image-4375" src="http://brevitymag.com/wp-content/uploads/2015/09/Shoes.jpg" alt="Shoes" width="300" height="454" />After getting booted from high school three times, I joined the military. Three years into my enlistment, the Navy cut me loose. I moved back to Pennsylvania and got married, but then my wife split, taking our baby boy with her. I was a 24-year-old cyclone of poor decisions.</p>
<p align="left">In time, I landed in county jail. At least nobody gets thrown out of jail. Drug treatment followed, but even that didn't work: I went to AA meetings high. One night a woman named Alice pulled me aside and hissed: "You are going to die!"</p>
<p align="left">I told her the obvious: "We're all going to die, Alice."</p>
Another court date loomed. Without treatment, the judge would put me in jail. The rehabs in Pennsylvania wouldn't take me but suggested a facility in the Bronx. New York City seemed like a long shot, another poor decision. Without options, I took the Greyhound to Times Square.

At dawn, I went to a drug bazaar in Alphabet City. My last fix, my last twenty dollars. I walked to 99th and Amsterdam for an intake appointment—my last stop before the Bronx. Around 3pm, a Puerto Rican named Americo started my paperwork. He had greasy hair and asked the last time I got high. I was nervous and thought a joke might lighten the mood.

"What time is it now?" I asked.

"You got high today?" Americo scowled. Instead of sending me to the Bronx, he sent me to a shelter downtown. "Get outta here," he said.

I went to Saint Mark's Place in the East Village. About a dozen homeless people wandered about in a cavernous room with soaring black walls, large hand-painted hippie flowers, and purple peace signs.

"What is this place?" I asked.

"The Electric Circus," said a slight Latino man with glassy eyes. "A night club from the 60s. Hendrix played here." A disco ball hung from the ceiling and fold out cots were clustered in twos and threes on the dance floor. One thing was certain: Jimi didn't play here anymore.

Food was scarce. Weekdays everyone would sit on the front steps to ask passers-by for change. I couldn't bring myself to beg. At the corner deli, I slipped two ice cream sandwiches into my jacket.

"You," a tousle-headed man from behind the counter said. "Put those back."
<p align="left">I feigned innocence, but his dark eyes shone fiercely. "The ice cream in your jacket," he said. "Put it back."</p>
I did as he requested and headed for the door.

"You hungry?" he asked. Without waiting for an answer, he sailed an oven soft roll over the counter toward me. His kindness made my face burn with shame.

Weekends they held dances to earn money for the shelter. These lasted until 3 or 4am and you couldn't setup your cot until after. I just wanted to hide from all the handsome people, so I went to the basement, which everyone called the Dom. I was told the Dom was Andy Warhol's, "Exploding Plastic Inevitable," as if this explained everything. Now the Dom was home to round-the-clock AA meetings.

At one meeting, the chairperson started reading the literature, but then he got up and headed to the back of the room. An old homeless man had fallen asleep with a cigar, setting his overcoat ablaze. The chairperson stopped reading long enough to swat the flames out. Good God, I thought.

In Pennsylvania, I had boosted a pair of Nikes: hi-top leather, white on white, my favorite kind of sneaker. I considered swapping these to another homeless guy who may have had some dope. As I was trying to decide what to do, the person in charge at the shelter, a beautiful Puerto Rican woman with an ugly scar that ran from the left side of her mouth all the way to her ear (this meant she had snitched), asked everyone to help decorate the Christmas tree.

Someone had rescued a pathetic little plastic tree from the trash. There were no ornaments or lights: just newspaper folded into origami and some macaroni noodles threaded with string.

I decided it was beneath me.

Sitting in the corner, I cupped my hands to light a cigarette. The wind began to rise. If everything worked out exactly the way I wanted—best case scenario—I would be high for a few hours, and then…

I would be barefoot.

In the city.

In December.

I decided I had better start decorating that ugly little tree.
<p align="left">---</p>
<p align="left"><strong>Tim Elhajj</strong>'s work has appeared in<a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2008/06/15/fashion/15love.html?partner=permalink&amp;exprod=permalink" target="_blank"> Modern Love</a> and a special <a href="http://www.creativenonfiction.org/brevity/brev27/elhajj_iam.html" target="_blank">summer bonus</a> edition of Brevity 27. Currently in a homemade, self-imposed witness protection program, Tim is hard at work on a coming-of-age memoir. He takes frequent breaks to write about his elementary school kids, parenting, and a past life shooting dope.</p>
<p style="text-align: right;" align="left">photo by <a href="http://kristin.fouquet.cc/" target="_blank">Kristin Fouquet</a></p>]]></content:encoded>
		<excerpt:encoded><![CDATA[]]></excerpt:encoded>
		<wp:post_id>4459</wp:post_id>
		<wp:post_date><![CDATA[2009-01-12 05:54:49]]></wp:post_date>
		<wp:post_date_gmt><![CDATA[2009-01-12 10:54:49]]></wp:post_date_gmt>
		<wp:comment_status><![CDATA[open]]></wp:comment_status>
		<wp:ping_status><![CDATA[open]]></wp:ping_status>
		<wp:post_name><![CDATA[jimi-dont-play-here-no-more]]></wp:post_name>
		<wp:status><![CDATA[publish]]></wp:status>
		<wp:post_parent>0</wp:post_parent>
		<wp:menu_order>0</wp:menu_order>
		<wp:post_type><![CDATA[post]]></wp:post_type>
		<wp:post_password><![CDATA[]]></wp:post_password>
		<wp:is_sticky>0</wp:is_sticky>
		<category domain="post_tag" nicename="addiction"><![CDATA[addiction]]></category>
		<category domain="category" nicename="issue-29-january-2009"><![CDATA[Issue 29 / January 2009]]></category>
		<category domain="post_tag" nicename="memoir"><![CDATA[Memoir]]></category>
		<category domain="category" nicename="nonfiction"><![CDATA[Nonfiction]]></category>
		<category domain="post_tag" nicename="persona"><![CDATA[persona]]></category>
		<category domain="post_tag" nicename="setting"><![CDATA[setting]]></category>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key><![CDATA[_edit_last]]></wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[2]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key><![CDATA[Author]]></wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[TIM ELHAJJ]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
	</item>
	<item>
		<title>Future Ex Buys Pajamas</title>
		<link>http://brevitymag.com/nonfiction/future-ex-buys-pajamas/</link>
		<pubDate>Wed, 14 Jan 2009 10:50:51 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[elhajj]]></dc:creator>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://brevitymag.com/?p=4461</guid>
		<description></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p align="left"><img class="alignright size-full wp-image-4373" src="http://brevitymag.com/wp-content/uploads/2015/09/Mannequin.jpg" alt="Mannequin" width="300" height="456" />We begin our descent somewhere over Normandy when I read in <em>Let's Go! France</em> that the Eiffel Tower is this beacon for suicide. Host to twelve successful attempts every year. Katja tells me the jumpers tend not to be locals. She says no Parisian would be caught dead anywhere near the Eiffel Tower, and by the end of the first day I know that she's right.</p>
<p align="left">Still, I want to see the tower right away. Just as soon as we get off the plane. I want to confirm its existence and fortify mine. Tourism is the only religion I've got. My faith rests comfortably in shiny hotels with walk-in thermostatic showers that fire at the body from six different angles. Katja and I ride the tower elevator a thousand feet into the sky with a group of very elderly Americans. They advise us to be on the alert for nausea and pickpockets, and to drink plenty of fluids.</p>
<p align="left">Parisians. They murmur like little doves. They cluck and they coo. No matter how long we end up living here, I know I'll never learn to speak that way. And I understand, too, from the moment we arrive, that Parisians are too discrete to hurl themselves from international landmarks.</p>
<p align="left">We walk along Rue de Grenelle, it's this teeming neighborhood street where shopkeepers shake hands with customers. Everybody knows everybody. Everybody knows French. I can't imagine learning French by living here any more than by living in the sea I could learn not to drown.</p>
<p align="left">The more we walk, the more difficult it becomes to avoid mention of the city's high concentration of lingerie boutiques. During one fifteen minute stretch we pass more lingerie shops than pharmacies. For every chicken roasting on a spit, there's sexy lingerie smoldering in the boutique window next door. I try to be a man about it. Try not to stare. But every time a woman emerges from a lingerie shop, I can't resist studying her face for signs of lifelong erotic contentment.</p>
<p align="left">Katja approaches the window of a designer lingerie boutique, so high-end there's hardly any merchandise at all. Every item has the delicate vascularity of a burning leaf. Her eyes settle on a pair of black stockings.</p>
<p align="left">Where I grew up, they sold women's underwear by the six-pack. They lashed ill-fitting underpants to mannequins with screw-on body parts and staked them over sale-bins like scarecrows. I feel lacking in some essential training that French men are required to undergo before they're allowed access to public life. Some sort of erotic inurement. When I ask Katja if French men are circumcised, her glance betrays this dwindling reserve of pity.</p>
<p align="left">She says the USA is the only nation in the world that practices genital mutilation on men, and segues into one of her pet theses: that I am, without knowing it, the victim of my own manhood. That somehow, having been circumcised, having been exposed to too much pornography too early in life, having lost teeth in fights, having a tendency to drive cars offensively, that somehow all this makes me a victim. I don't feel like a victim.</p>

<div align="left">I imagine the stockings on her. I imagine her toes dipping into this shimmering pool of silk. Her slender fingers gathering the material, a slow unfurling around the calf, a tautness at the upper thigh. A second skin transforming us both. And then I notice something. Suspended behind the stockings, hanging from a pink padded hanger like a wet blanket, one pair of women's pajamas. The anti-lingerie. And I worry about this. I worry that when women speak of comfort, of pajamas, of down-filled comforters topped with thirty-eight matching throw pillows, what they're really talking about is relief. Meanwhile, the Parisians murmur. They cluck and they coo. I can't understand a word they're saying.</div>
<p align="left">---</p>
<p align="left"><strong>John Bresland </strong>works in radio, video, and print. His essays have aired on public radio, and his video essays can now be seen at<a href="http://www.ninthletter.com/featured_artist/artist/9" target="_blank"> Ninth Letter </a>and <a href="http://www.blackbird.vcu.edu/v4n1/gallery/bresland/index.htm" target="_blank">Blackbird</a> online. His print essays can be read in <em>North American Review, Hotel Amerika, Minnesota Monthly</em> and elsewhere. He is an artist-in-residence at Northwestern University, where he teaches creative writing and new media.</p>
<p align="center">**[Hear John Bresland's <strong>audio version</strong> and
why he wanted this essay to be experienced as audio:
<a href="http://brevity.wordpress.com/" target="_blank">John Bresland on the Brevity Blog </a>]</p>
<p style="text-align: right;" align="center">photo by <a href="http://kristin.fouquet.cc/" target="_blank">Kristin Fouquet</a></p>]]></content:encoded>
		<excerpt:encoded><![CDATA[]]></excerpt:encoded>
		<wp:post_id>4461</wp:post_id>
		<wp:post_date><![CDATA[2009-01-14 05:50:51]]></wp:post_date>
		<wp:post_date_gmt><![CDATA[2009-01-14 10:50:51]]></wp:post_date_gmt>
		<wp:comment_status><![CDATA[open]]></wp:comment_status>
		<wp:ping_status><![CDATA[open]]></wp:ping_status>
		<wp:post_name><![CDATA[future-ex-buys-pajamas]]></wp:post_name>
		<wp:status><![CDATA[publish]]></wp:status>
		<wp:post_parent>0</wp:post_parent>
		<wp:menu_order>0</wp:menu_order>
		<wp:post_type><![CDATA[post]]></wp:post_type>
		<wp:post_password><![CDATA[]]></wp:post_password>
		<wp:is_sticky>0</wp:is_sticky>
		<category domain="post_tag" nicename="beginningsendings"><![CDATA[beginnings/endings]]></category>
		<category domain="post_tag" nicename="characterization"><![CDATA[characterization]]></category>
		<category domain="post_tag" nicename="gendersexuality"><![CDATA[gender/sexuality]]></category>
		<category domain="post_tag" nicename="imagery"><![CDATA[imagery]]></category>
		<category domain="category" nicename="issue-29-january-2009"><![CDATA[Issue 29 / January 2009]]></category>
		<category domain="post_tag" nicename="loverelationships"><![CDATA[love/relationships]]></category>
		<category domain="category" nicename="nonfiction"><![CDATA[Nonfiction]]></category>
		<category domain="post_tag" nicename="sensory_detail"><![CDATA[sensory_detail]]></category>
		<category domain="post_tag" nicename="speculation"><![CDATA[speculation]]></category>
		<category domain="post_tag" nicename="travel"><![CDATA[travel]]></category>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key><![CDATA[_edit_last]]></wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[2]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key><![CDATA[Author]]></wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[JOHN BRESLAND]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
	</item>
	<item>
		<title>You Like It Don&#039;t You, You Like It Hard and Cold</title>
		<link>http://brevitymag.com/nonfiction/you-like-it-dont-you-you-like-it-hard-and-cold/</link>
		<pubDate>Wed, 07 Jan 2009 10:54:46 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[elhajj]]></dc:creator>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://brevitymag.com/?p=4463</guid>
		<description></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p align="left"><img class="alignright size-full wp-image-4381" src="http://brevitymag.com/wp-content/uploads/2015/09/WrenchGirlcloseup.jpg" alt="WrenchGirlcloseup" width="300" height="400" />and sweet with surprises inside well let me introduce you to the state line dairy where the cherries in the sherbet are harvested from virgins and the girls filling the cones all have boyfriends in vietnam and the thing in the jar on the counter is a pickled pig's foot let me introduce you to bob's country club there is no bob or everyone's bob there are french fries and the juke box is all mahalia and mary wells and mrs. bob is frying whities easing them down into the grease and the dance floor is empty but for bob and the ghosts or you and me in a short short skirt and underpants from the kresge's that is now a bingo hall let me introduce you to the happy house a good plate of chop suey and the old ladies playing cards in the corner it burned last weekend and now the egg rolls are ash and the pagoda and the neon calligraphy let me show you where i peed see how the ashes meet the woods see the trillium sticking up like window peekers have you ever seen a chinese place with buttered dinner roles and funeral home placemats you like it sweet and cold and creamy you like it sweet and cold and creamy and hard you like it with a spoon have you tried it with a small wooden paddle have you tried it down where the indians are buried have you tried it with an arrowhead poking you in the ass have you eaten it with your hands how about sobbing have you swallowed it cold and creamy and hard and hollow and the rock salt still steaming in the grinder.</p>
<p align="left">---</p>
<p align="left"><strong>Diane Seuss</strong> is Writer in Residence at Kalamazoo College.  Recent work has appeared or is forthcoming in <em>The Georgia Review, The North American Review, Indiana Review, Cimarron Review</em> and <em>Alaska Quarterly Review</em>.  New Issues Press published her book <a href="http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/0932826652?ie=UTF8&amp;tag=brevitynonfic-20&amp;linkCode=as2&amp;camp=1789&amp;creative=390957&amp;creativeASIN=0932826652" target="_blank">It Blows You Hollow</a><img src="http://www.assoc-amazon.com/e/ir?t=brevitynonfic-20&amp;l=as2&amp;o=1&amp;a=0932826652" alt="" width="1" height="1" border="0" />, and she has work in the anthologies <em><a href="http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/0877456879?ie=UTF8&amp;tag=brevitynonfic-20&amp;linkCode=as2&amp;camp=1789&amp;creative=390957&amp;creativeASIN=0877456879" target="_blank">Boomer Girls: Poems by Women from the Baby Boom Generation</a><img src="http://www.assoc-amazon.com/e/ir?t=brevitynonfic-20&amp;l=as2&amp;o=1&amp;a=0877456879" alt="" width="1" height="1" border="0" />, Are You Experienced</em> and <em>Sweeping Beauty</em>, all from the University of Iowa Press.</p>
<p style="text-align: right;" align="left"><span style="font-size: small;">photo by <a href="http://kristin.fouquet.cc/" target="_blank">Kristin Fouquet</a></span></p>]]></content:encoded>
		<excerpt:encoded><![CDATA[]]></excerpt:encoded>
		<wp:post_id>4463</wp:post_id>
		<wp:post_date><![CDATA[2009-01-07 05:54:46]]></wp:post_date>
		<wp:post_date_gmt><![CDATA[2009-01-07 10:54:46]]></wp:post_date_gmt>
		<wp:comment_status><![CDATA[open]]></wp:comment_status>
		<wp:ping_status><![CDATA[open]]></wp:ping_status>
		<wp:post_name><![CDATA[you-like-it-dont-you-you-like-it-hard-and-cold]]></wp:post_name>
		<wp:status><![CDATA[publish]]></wp:status>
		<wp:post_parent>0</wp:post_parent>
		<wp:menu_order>0</wp:menu_order>
		<wp:post_type><![CDATA[post]]></wp:post_type>
		<wp:post_password><![CDATA[]]></wp:post_password>
		<wp:is_sticky>0</wp:is_sticky>
		<category domain="post_tag" nicename="beginningsendings"><![CDATA[beginnings/endings]]></category>
		<category domain="post_tag" nicename="experimental_form"><![CDATA[experimental_form]]></category>
		<category domain="post_tag" nicename="food"><![CDATA[food]]></category>
		<category domain="post_tag" nicename="gendersexuality"><![CDATA[gender/sexuality]]></category>
		<category domain="category" nicename="issue-29-january-2009"><![CDATA[Issue 29 / January 2009]]></category>
		<category domain="post_tag" nicename="lyric_essay"><![CDATA[lyric_essay]]></category>
		<category domain="category" nicename="nonfiction"><![CDATA[Nonfiction]]></category>
		<category domain="post_tag" nicename="voice"><![CDATA[voice]]></category>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key><![CDATA[_edit_last]]></wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[2]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key><![CDATA[Author]]></wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[DIANE SEUSS]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
	</item>
	<item>
		<title>Cathy or Katy</title>
		<link>http://brevitymag.com/nonfiction/cathy-or-katy/</link>
		<pubDate>Thu, 08 Jan 2009 10:54:43 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[elhajj]]></dc:creator>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://brevitymag.com/?p=4465</guid>
		<description></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p align="left"><img class="alignright size-full wp-image-4374" src="http://brevitymag.com/wp-content/uploads/2015/09/MirrorMirror.jpg" alt="MirrorMirror" width="400" height="297" />The rain fell through bus headlights, getting us ready for the big lie.  We spent the weekend in New York City, my heart beating up through my neck in the gold glow and enormous doors of the Mayflower Hotel.  Eric and I, when the urge to crawl out of myself toward her became no longer strange but strange and terrifying, left to cruise Manhattan, ending in a topless bar with hardcore sex moaning from each TV in the corners, where one of the dancers after having danced and swung her breasts before me gently and rhythmically, sat next to me and asked why I was in New York and (patting my thigh) honey would I like to buy her a drink?  Eric (two months later he mounted an unconscious girl drunk on beer and gin in a motel room in Ocean City, Maryland  because he didn't think anyone was watching) wouldn't move his gaze from the television, so I creaked something about a journalism convention.  I said no.  She glanced at the bartender who removed our watered-down, over-priced beer and asked for ID.  We left.</p>
<p align="left">Later that night I stared at Cathy or Katy and the thousands of freckles on her cheeks, the way her loose hair caught light from the desk lamp by the bed as if each strand were alight and moving, and imagined the soft dark inside her baggy sweatshirt and the way she would look through me and say my name or ask my name and realizing then that she had a brother and a father.  She sat utterly unkempt, breaking my heart with every shift of her leg, or sip of her drink. Mike got a date with Cathy's or Katy's friend, whom everyone thought was prettiest.  I don't remember the bus ride home, or much of the following weeks, when my fingers would tremble as I phoned her, and I'd ache in the surprise she expressed each time she knew it was me.</p>
<p align="left">So I called less and less.  I was relieved when I lost her number.  I drove past what I thought was her house, and I wished I could be her brother, who endeared himself to her in so many domestic ways, his bedroom down the hall from hers, the way he answered the phone.  What I recall: rain through bus headlights in the parking lot, with my house sitting down the hill.  March.  The rain fell as if on a great swell, and I looked, I thought, and saw ahead of me, over Cathy's or Katy's head of red hair, and saw little else.</p>
<p align="left">The memory hole.  Who, what, when, where, why. Cathy, or Katy.  <em>A faint whiff of Catholic schoolgirl gleam-in-eye a peek down a white blouse a pale blue bra.</em>  Did I meet her mother?  Or was that someone else.</p>
<p align="left">I caught fourteen sunfish on one bright, mythic afternoon.  That I know.</p>
<p align="left">I obsess on the motivation of my friend Eric who mounted an unconscious girl drunk on beer and gin in a motel room in Ocean City.  A filthy beach house at three a.m., and I wonder if I really was there, in an adjacent bed, feigning sleep under pale blue sheets while on the floor beneath me, between the beds, Eric quietly laid on top of a girl and did what the hallways later said he did.  Or did I hear the tale months later.  Or imagine the whole thing.</p>
I recall when my younger brother was born: a mother in a red pony-tail, a pale blue package, a tenuous smile in a garish photo.  My parents said it never happened, I was never there.  There.  There's the photo to prove the memory correct, just as it happened, as I promised.
<p align="left">---</p>
<p align="left"><a href="mailto:joe.bonomo@yahoo.com"><strong>Joe Bonomo</strong></a> is the author of <a href="http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/014311395X?ie=UTF8&amp;tag=brevitynonfic-20&amp;linkCode=as2&amp;camp=1789&amp;creative=390957&amp;creativeASIN=014311395X" target="_blank">Installations </a><img src="http://www.assoc-amazon.com/e/ir?t=brevitynonfic-20&amp;l=as2&amp;o=1&amp;a=014311395X" alt="" width="1" height="1" border="0" /> (Penguin, 2008), <a href="http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/0826428460?ie=UTF8&amp;tag=brevitynonfic-20&amp;linkCode=as2&amp;camp=1789&amp;creative=390957&amp;creativeASIN=0826428460" target="_blank">Sweat: The Story of the Fleshtones, America's Garage Band</a><img src="http://www.assoc-amazon.com/e/ir?t=brevitynonfic-20&amp;l=as2&amp;o=1&amp;a=0826428460" alt="" width="1" height="1" border="0" />(Continuum, 2007), and <em>Jerry Lee Lewis: Lost &amp; Found</em> (Continuum, forthcoming 2009). Recently listed in “Notable Essays” in<em> Best American Essays</em>, his prose appears in <em>Fourth Genre, New Ohio Review, Storyscape, Hotel Amerika</em>, and the “Lyric Essay” issue of <em>Seneca Review</em>.  He’s at work on a collection of autobiographical essays, and teaches at Northern Illinois University.</p>
<p style="text-align: right;" align="left">photo by <a href="http://kristin.fouquet.cc/" target="_blank">Kristin Fouquet</a></p>]]></content:encoded>
		<excerpt:encoded><![CDATA[]]></excerpt:encoded>
		<wp:post_id>4465</wp:post_id>
		<wp:post_date><![CDATA[2009-01-08 05:54:43]]></wp:post_date>
		<wp:post_date_gmt><![CDATA[2009-01-08 10:54:43]]></wp:post_date_gmt>
		<wp:comment_status><![CDATA[open]]></wp:comment_status>
		<wp:ping_status><![CDATA[open]]></wp:ping_status>
		<wp:post_name><![CDATA[cathy-or-katy]]></wp:post_name>
		<wp:status><![CDATA[publish]]></wp:status>
		<wp:post_parent>0</wp:post_parent>
		<wp:menu_order>0</wp:menu_order>
		<wp:post_type><![CDATA[post]]></wp:post_type>
		<wp:post_password><![CDATA[]]></wp:post_password>
		<wp:is_sticky>0</wp:is_sticky>
		<category domain="post_tag" nicename="cityurban"><![CDATA[city/urban]]></category>
		<category domain="category" nicename="issue-29-january-2009"><![CDATA[Issue 29 / January 2009]]></category>
		<category domain="post_tag" nicename="loverelationships"><![CDATA[love/relationships]]></category>
		<category domain="post_tag" nicename="lyric_essay"><![CDATA[lyric_essay]]></category>
		<category domain="post_tag" nicename="meditation"><![CDATA[meditation]]></category>
		<category domain="post_tag" nicename="memoir"><![CDATA[Memoir]]></category>
		<category domain="category" nicename="nonfiction"><![CDATA[Nonfiction]]></category>
		<category domain="post_tag" nicename="persona"><![CDATA[persona]]></category>
		<category domain="post_tag" nicename="setting"><![CDATA[setting]]></category>
		<category domain="post_tag" nicename="speculation"><![CDATA[speculation]]></category>
		<category domain="post_tag" nicename="tone"><![CDATA[tone]]></category>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key><![CDATA[_edit_last]]></wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[2]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key><![CDATA[Author]]></wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[JOE BONOMO]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
	</item>
	<item>
		<title>Suspended</title>
		<link>http://brevitymag.com/nonfiction/suspended/</link>
		<pubDate>Sun, 11 Jan 2009 10:54:41 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[elhajj]]></dc:creator>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://brevitymag.com/?p=4467</guid>
		<description></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p align="left"><img class="alignright size-full wp-image-4368" src="http://brevitymag.com/wp-content/uploads/2015/09/ChairPigeon.jpg" alt="ChairPigeon" width="400" height="300" />The locker room walls were painted puke green and lined like a cage with metal hooks, and red mesh equipment bags hung from the hooks like meat. One of the bags was swinging, and I was swinging in it, and Drew McKinnick slapped at it and did his punching, and the janitor got me down.</p>
<p align="left">What did my father say to the principal, and how many times had he said how many things? My boy is not eighty pounds yet. My boy is in the seventh grade. My boy is not a linebacker. Can’t you see I love my boy? If you had a boy to love what would you not do?</p>
<p align="left">What did the principal say to my father? Did he say he had a boy and the boy got caught drinking in the tenth grade and he kicked his own boy out of school, same as anybody else? Did he tell my father what he told us once a year when they brought the boys into the gymnasium and left the girls away? <em>I loved and love my wife, and she is not my ex-wife, not praise Jesus in the eyes of God, despite her running off with the Navy captain, despite it all I wait and wait and one day she will be restored to me. I know it in my heart of faith, I wait as Hosea waited, now let us pray.</em></p>
<p align="left">Whatever passed or did not pass between them, this once it did not matter how much money McKinnick’s father gave the school, or how many animals he had veterinaried to health, or how many ordinances he had sealed with his mayor’s seal. This once I came home beaten and bruised and told my father, “They suspended him for three days.”</p>
<p align="left">That night I slept and dreamt of three days free of red ears flicked blood red and slapped until I heard the ocean. The bathroom was mine to piss in, free of fear of footsteps from behind, one hand in my hair and the other on my belt, the painful lifting, then my head beneath the commode water.</p>
<p align="left">That afternoon I skip-stepped to the bus, the Florida sun high and hot, and this once thinking the heat balmy and tropical rather than stalking and oppressive. Then, somewhere between the Route 7 and the Route 8, somebody grabbed me by the collar and slammed me against the black bumper. At first I thought it was him, because it looked like him, same dog teeth, same mocking smile, but bigger somehow, and how had it been kept from me he had an older brother?</p>
<p align="left">“You think you’re something,” he said, and lifted me until my feet were off the ground. He was as big as my father. “You ever run crying on my brother again, I’ll beat you within an inch of your life, you hear me? I wouldn’t mind breaking you.”</p>
<p align="left">He had me up against the back of the bus, and somewhere somebody had taught him how to do it, and his brother, too. I can see their faces now, but younger, fleshier, their father pressing their bodies to the wall, and then, older, leaner, their sons looking down at their fathers in their fear, learning.</p>
<p align="left">---</p>
<p align="left"><strong>Kyle Minor's </strong>recent work appears in <em>The Southern Review, The Gettysburg Review, Twentysomething Essays by Twentysomething Writers</em>, and <a href="http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/0618812679?ie=UTF8&amp;tag=brevitynonfic-20&amp;linkCode=as2&amp;camp=1789&amp;creative=390957&amp;creativeASIN=0618812679" target="_blank">The Best American Mystery Stories 2008</a> . He is Visiting Writer at the University of Toledo and author of <a href="http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/0979312361?ie=UTF8&amp;tag=brevitynonfic-20&amp;linkCode=as2&amp;camp=1789&amp;creative=390957&amp;creativeASIN=0979312361" target="_blank">In the Devil's Territory,</a><img src="http://www.assoc-amazon.com/e/ir?t=brevitynonfic-20&amp;l=as2&amp;o=1&amp;a=0979312361" alt="" width="1" height="1" border="0" /> a collection of short fiction.</p>
<p style="text-align: right;" align="left">photo by <a href="http://kristin.fouquet.cc/" target="_blank">Kristin Fouquet</a></p>]]></content:encoded>
		<excerpt:encoded><![CDATA[]]></excerpt:encoded>
		<wp:post_id>4467</wp:post_id>
		<wp:post_date><![CDATA[2009-01-11 05:54:41]]></wp:post_date>
		<wp:post_date_gmt><![CDATA[2009-01-11 10:54:41]]></wp:post_date_gmt>
		<wp:comment_status><![CDATA[open]]></wp:comment_status>
		<wp:ping_status><![CDATA[open]]></wp:ping_status>
		<wp:post_name><![CDATA[suspended]]></wp:post_name>
		<wp:status><![CDATA[publish]]></wp:status>
		<wp:post_parent>0</wp:post_parent>
		<wp:menu_order>0</wp:menu_order>
		<wp:post_type><![CDATA[post]]></wp:post_type>
		<wp:post_password><![CDATA[]]></wp:post_password>
		<wp:is_sticky>0</wp:is_sticky>
		<category domain="post_tag" nicename="beginningsendings"><![CDATA[beginnings/endings]]></category>
		<category domain="post_tag" nicename="characterization"><![CDATA[characterization]]></category>
		<category domain="post_tag" nicename="childhoodfamily"><![CDATA[childhood/family]]></category>
		<category domain="post_tag" nicename="education"><![CDATA[education]]></category>
		<category domain="post_tag" nicename="imagery"><![CDATA[imagery]]></category>
		<category domain="category" nicename="issue-29-january-2009"><![CDATA[Issue 29 / January 2009]]></category>
		<category domain="post_tag" nicename="memoir"><![CDATA[Memoir]]></category>
		<category domain="category" nicename="nonfiction"><![CDATA[Nonfiction]]></category>
		<category domain="post_tag" nicename="parenting"><![CDATA[parenting]]></category>
		<category domain="post_tag" nicename="speculation"><![CDATA[speculation]]></category>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key><![CDATA[_edit_last]]></wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[2]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key><![CDATA[Author]]></wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[KYLE MINOR]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
	</item>
	<item>
		<title>The Crab in the Stars</title>
		<link>http://brevitymag.com/nonfiction/the-crab-in-the-stars/</link>
		<pubDate>Thu, 08 Jan 2009 10:54:37 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[elhajj]]></dc:creator>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://brevitymag.com/?p=4469</guid>
		<description></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p align="left"><img class="alignright size-full wp-image-4376" src="http://brevitymag.com/wp-content/uploads/2015/09/TombTopper.jpg" alt="TombTopper" width="300" height="388" />I am home alone—sort of.  I am almost twelve, and I am unsupervised.  My parents have gone shopping.  My brother is at a friend's.  It's just me and my grandparents, who live in an apartment attached to our house.</p>
My grandfather is sick.  He has been for a year.  For a few weeks now he has hardly eaten, and for a few days he has been unable to blink, so my grandmother applies tears to his eyes.

On this day I am not thinking of his sickness.  I am writing a fantasy novel called <em>The Tempest</em>.  (I have heard this name somewhere but have not yet read Shakespeare, do not realize that this name is taken.)  My <em>Tempest</em> is about an evil wizard who steals horses from girls who are lucky enough to own them in the first place.

Someone knocks at the door while I am writing, and I answer it.  It is a man with a clipboard.  He is wearing a bicycle helmet.  When he speaks I know he is retarded.  I can't understand him, but I know I must try.  My mother is an occupational therapist who works with retarded people and she has made this clear to me.  He wants me to sign something on his clipboard.  He is saying something about Carl Sagan and Russia and exploring space, something about weapons and the Cold War, (which will end within the year, though we don't know that yet.)  I can tell that he is reciting a script and I wonder if he is leaving things out, because the words make sense but the sentences do not.  Finally I tell him, "No thanks," and I shut the door, wondering what happened.  I want to tell someone, so I go down the half-flight of stairs to my grandparents' apartment.

My grandmother is just standing there.

"You should have seen the guy," I tell her, and she shushes me.

"He's dead," she says, and we stare at each other for a moment.

"Can I see him?" I say.

She leads me into the bedroom, and there he is, blood on the pillow next to his mouth.  He has shrunken so much that his limbs no longer fill out the leg holes of his underpants, and they sag, revealing too much.  I look at his face, and I wonder if he closed his own eyes or if my grandmother did it for him.  I wonder if she was with him when he died.

She pulls me into the hallway.

"The coroner is coming.  So is your uncle," she says.  (My parents will not own cell phones for another ten years, so we cannot call them to come too.)  We wait.  I go upstairs to wait by the dining room window.  Years later, I will wonder why I left her to wait alone.

The coroner arrives first, then my uncle, but I do not move from the window.  I do not see what happens in the bedroom, but I see what they carry back out to the van.

My parents arrive after the coroner has gone, and I go out to tell my mother what has happened.  I can't speak.  I stand in front of her on the driveway and she sees it in my face.  She pulls me into her arms and starts to cry.

I do not cry yet.  At the funeral I will cry because the minister will not have drawn her lipstick on within the arcs that define her lips, making a mess of her face, and I will cry because my cousins will laugh at her.  Perhaps it is funny, but I will cry anyway because I will want meaning in a world that seems absurd.

Now that my mother knows her father is dead, I want to tell her about the retarded man, too.  I know she won't care now, but I can't stop thinking about him.  I imagine that he was the angel of death, from a star within the constellation of Cancer.  He was a crab creature disguised as a person, still learning to form words with his human mouth, which was why his speech sounded funny.  He didn't know who Carl Sagan was any more than I did; it was just something he heard in a transmission that he picked up in space.  There was no scythe and cloak, but he was the angel of death.  I opened the door and let him in.
<p align="left">---</p>
<p align="left"><a href="mailto:lsmatter@gmail.com"><strong>Laura Sewell Matter</strong></a> is a high school teacher in Albuquerque, New Mexico.  Her work has appeared in <em>The Georgia Review</em> and <a href="http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/0393330249?ie=UTF8&amp;tag=brevitynonfic-20&amp;linkCode=as2&amp;camp=1789&amp;creative=390957&amp;creativeASIN=0393330249" target="_blank">The Best Creative Nonfiction Vol. 2</a><img src="http://www.assoc-amazon.com/e/ir?t=brevitynonfic-20&amp;l=as2&amp;o=1&amp;a=0393330249" alt="" width="1" height="1" border="0" /> , and is forthcoming in <em>Aethlon: The Journal of Sports Literature.</em>  Any day now, she will complete her MFA at the University of New Mexico.</p>
<p style="text-align: right;" align="left">photo by <a href="http://kristin.fouquet.cc/" target="_blank">Kristin Fouquet</a></p>]]></content:encoded>
		<excerpt:encoded><![CDATA[]]></excerpt:encoded>
		<wp:post_id>4469</wp:post_id>
		<wp:post_date><![CDATA[2009-01-08 05:54:37]]></wp:post_date>
		<wp:post_date_gmt><![CDATA[2009-01-08 10:54:37]]></wp:post_date_gmt>
		<wp:comment_status><![CDATA[open]]></wp:comment_status>
		<wp:ping_status><![CDATA[open]]></wp:ping_status>
		<wp:post_name><![CDATA[the-crab-in-the-stars]]></wp:post_name>
		<wp:status><![CDATA[publish]]></wp:status>
		<wp:post_parent>0</wp:post_parent>
		<wp:menu_order>0</wp:menu_order>
		<wp:post_type><![CDATA[post]]></wp:post_type>
		<wp:post_password><![CDATA[]]></wp:post_password>
		<wp:is_sticky>0</wp:is_sticky>
		<category domain="post_tag" nicename="aging"><![CDATA[aging]]></category>
		<category domain="post_tag" nicename="childhoodfamily"><![CDATA[childhood/family]]></category>
		<category domain="post_tag" nicename="death"><![CDATA[Death]]></category>
		<category domain="post_tag" nicename="frame"><![CDATA[frame]]></category>
		<category domain="post_tag" nicename="illnessdisability"><![CDATA[illness/disability]]></category>
		<category domain="category" nicename="issue-29-january-2009"><![CDATA[Issue 29 / January 2009]]></category>
		<category domain="post_tag" nicename="memoir"><![CDATA[Memoir]]></category>
		<category domain="category" nicename="nonfiction"><![CDATA[Nonfiction]]></category>
		<category domain="post_tag" nicename="setting"><![CDATA[setting]]></category>
		<category domain="post_tag" nicename="voice"><![CDATA[voice]]></category>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key><![CDATA[_edit_last]]></wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[2]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key><![CDATA[Author]]></wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[LAURA SEWELL MATTER]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
	</item>
	<item>
		<title>Tenderness</title>
		<link>http://brevitymag.com/nonfiction/tenderness/</link>
		<pubDate>Fri, 09 Jan 2009 10:54:34 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[elhajj]]></dc:creator>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://brevitymag.com/?p=4472</guid>
		<description></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p align="left"><img class="alignright size-full wp-image-4378" src="http://brevitymag.com/wp-content/uploads/2015/09/Tree.jpg" alt="Tree" width="420" height="300" />Ronnie Thomley banged on our door early one morning. He runs heavy machinery for Willie Thrift, the pond man.</p>
<p align="left">He showed up at our place in the pine woods of panhandle Florida driving a compact air-conditioned tractor equipped with a front-loaded rotary cutter.  Ronnie's boss had sent him over to clear out some of the thick yaupon and gall berry bushes around the house to give our longleaf pines a fighting chance.</p>
<p align="left">Ronnie's longish hair stuck out from beneath the ubiquitous cap of the workingman, his dirty blonde mustache shot through with gray.  A potent mix of tobacco, diesel fuel and yesterday's work clothes entered the house fast as a stray cat when I opened the door. He politely turned down the offer of coffee. Ronnie was here to work.</p>
<p align="left">Ronnie ran that Cat for five hours. He tried his best to lift the blades when he saw a pine seedling, and saved any good hardwoods, too. Around 11:30, he stopped the giant machine for a smoke and was walking and talking with my husband, Buck, when I came around.</p>
<p align="left">Ronnie was telling a story about how he and his family used to live in a small cement block house at the end of the power line. Their home was a perennial target for vicious lightning strikes.</p>
<p align="left">"That lightning would make the whole house buzz and the light bulbs flicker. It would crackle all about. I would grab my two little girls and tell them to go<em>, right now</em>, and get under the bed. We would all just shake."</p>
<p align="left">The conversation turned to deer.  Ronnie lives even further out in the country than we do. About thirteen years ago, he was driving on a back road. Some guys were stopped where one of them had hit a doe with his pick-up truck. He stopped and went over to the scene. The doe was killed in the accident. As the men were standing around talking, Ronnie heard a weak bleating sound.</p>
<p align="left">"I went to look, and there was this tiny, baby deer, with the cord still attached. I felt so sorry for it; I didn't know what to do."</p>
<p align="left">He took the baby in his arms and brought it home.  There, he raised the doe, feeding her with a bottle. He made a bed for her in a box on the floor beside his own bed.</p>
<p align="left">The doe still stays in a fenced area by Ronnie's house. Each year in late January, he opens the gate. The doe goes out for a week or so, and then comes back in to his shelter. Each year, she gives birth to twins. She wears a bell so that other humans who might see her will realize she is not wild.</p>
<p align="left">"Most wild deer," he explained, "they don't live to be no older than twelve. I'm hoping she'll make it to sixteen."</p>
<p align="left">Ronnie feeds the old doe slices of sweet potato by hand every day.</p>
<p align="left">---</p>
<p align="left"><strong>Elizabeth Westmark</strong>'s essays have appeared in <em>The Emerald Coast Review XIV, Dead Mule School of Southern Literature, Muscadine Lines: A Southern Journal,</em> and the anthology <a href="http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/1933249005?ie=UTF8&amp;tag=brevitynonfic-20&amp;linkCode=as2&amp;camp=1789&amp;creative=390957&amp;creativeASIN=1933249005" target="_blank">Digital Dish: Five Seasons of the Freshest Recipes and Writing from Food Blogs Around the World.</a><img src="http://www.assoc-amazon.com/e/ir?t=brevitynonfic-20&amp;l=as2&amp;o=1&amp;a=1933249005" alt="" width="1" height="1" border="0" /> The former businesswoman blogs regularly on her <a href="http://www.switchedatbirth.us" target="_blank">website</a><em>.</em> She lives at her home, the Sanctuary at Longleaf Preserve, with her husband and chocolate lab.</p>
<p style="text-align: right;" align="left">photo by <a href="http://kristin.fouquet.cc/" target="_blank">Kristin Fouquet</a></p>]]></content:encoded>
		<excerpt:encoded><![CDATA[]]></excerpt:encoded>
		<wp:post_id>4472</wp:post_id>
		<wp:post_date><![CDATA[2009-01-09 05:54:34]]></wp:post_date>
		<wp:post_date_gmt><![CDATA[2009-01-09 10:54:34]]></wp:post_date_gmt>
		<wp:comment_status><![CDATA[open]]></wp:comment_status>
		<wp:ping_status><![CDATA[open]]></wp:ping_status>
		<wp:post_name><![CDATA[tenderness]]></wp:post_name>
		<wp:status><![CDATA[publish]]></wp:status>
		<wp:post_parent>0</wp:post_parent>
		<wp:menu_order>0</wp:menu_order>
		<wp:post_type><![CDATA[post]]></wp:post_type>
		<wp:post_password><![CDATA[]]></wp:post_password>
		<wp:is_sticky>0</wp:is_sticky>
		<category domain="post_tag" nicename="characterization"><![CDATA[characterization]]></category>
		<category domain="post_tag" nicename="class"><![CDATA[class]]></category>
		<category domain="post_tag" nicename="imagery"><![CDATA[imagery]]></category>
		<category domain="category" nicename="issue-29-january-2009"><![CDATA[Issue 29 / January 2009]]></category>
		<category domain="category" nicename="nonfiction"><![CDATA[Nonfiction]]></category>
		<category domain="post_tag" nicename="personal_essay"><![CDATA[personal_essay]]></category>
		<category domain="post_tag" nicename="rural_life"><![CDATA[rural_life]]></category>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key><![CDATA[_edit_last]]></wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[2]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key><![CDATA[Author]]></wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[ELIZABETH WESTMARK]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
	</item>
	<item>
		<title>Hill Street Blues</title>
		<link>http://brevitymag.com/nonfiction/hill-street-blues/</link>
		<pubDate>Sun, 11 Jan 2009 10:54:31 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[elhajj]]></dc:creator>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://brevitymag.com/?p=4474</guid>
		<description></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p align="left"><img class="alignright size-full wp-image-4370" src="http://brevitymag.com/wp-content/uploads/2015/09/Face.jpg" alt="Face" width="300" height="400" />My first memory fails me.  Brown shag carpet.  I am in the living room.  My mother is watching the end of <em>Hill Street Blues</em> on a color television.  She lights a cigarette.  Smoke rises, spiraling toward the ceiling.  When her show is over, an orange racecar with a Confederate flag painted over the top jumps into the air.  When it reaches the peak of its vertical climb, my mother turns off the television, stubs out her cigarette.  I cannot see my father, though I know that they are not yet divorced.</p>
<p align="left">No.  This is not my first memory.  I’m in the back seat of my parents’ car.  My father is driving my mother to work.  We live in Seattle.  It must be raining.  Yes, I can see it now.  It is raining.  Small beads of water stick to the glass of the windows.  My father looks at me in the rearview mirror.  He is smiling.  I see a sign for Pizza Hut.  <em>No, not tonight</em>, they tell me.  We drop off my mother.  I imagine my father kisses her before she takes the bus to work.</p>
<p align="left">No.  We are driving.  I am sitting in the back seat.  My mother is smoking.  When she notices I am watching her, she blows out small rings that rise toward the windshield.  We live in Seattle.  It is definitely raining.  I hum a song while tracing the beads of water with my fingers, trying to connect them.  I make images.  My father smiles at my mother when she asks me what I’m singing.  <em>Hill Street Blues</em>.</p>
<p align="left">We do not live in Seattle.  My mother and father are fighting in their bedroom in Great Falls, Montana.  My mother opens a package of cigarettes, and the clear cellophane tears around the box and spills out over their bed.  My father seems gentle.  He is pleading with her.  My mother screams.  She screams so loud my chest hurts.  She leaves the room and I hear the front door slam.  My father carries me in his arms.  We lie in bed watching television.  The glow flashes a prism across our faces.</p>

<div align="left">My father and I are alone.  This cannot be my first memory, but I remember it clearly.  The television is off.  We kneel on the soft blue carpet at the edge of his bed, praying for a mother.  Not my mother, who I seem to have forgotten, but someone who will take care of my father.  I close my eyes as hard as I can while he asks God for the woman he works with at my grandparents’ department store.  I notice the smell of my father’s deodorant, feel the warmth of his body.  His stubbled face grazes me.  I close my eyes harder.  My mother is gone. I imagine a cigarette, smoke rings expanding as they rise higher and higher.  Higher, I think, than I'll ever be able to reach.  I try to remember what she looks like.  I press my hands together.  I pray.  I’m afraid if I don’t concentrate, I’ll forget.</div>
<p align="left">---</p>
<p align="left"><strong>Bryan Fry</strong> is a husband and father of three children.  He earned his MFA in Creative Writing from the University of Idaho and is currently the co-editor of the online literary journal <em>Blood Orange Review</em>.  “Hill Street Blues” is the opening essay in the presently unpublished collection entitled <em>Between Here and There</em>, a personal narrative of being raised in Montana by a single father.  He lives in Pullman, WA.</p>
<p style="text-align: right;" align="left">photo by <a href="http://kristin.fouquet.cc/" target="_blank">Kristin Fouquet</a></p>]]></content:encoded>
		<excerpt:encoded><![CDATA[]]></excerpt:encoded>
		<wp:post_id>4474</wp:post_id>
		<wp:post_date><![CDATA[2009-01-11 05:54:31]]></wp:post_date>
		<wp:post_date_gmt><![CDATA[2009-01-11 10:54:31]]></wp:post_date_gmt>
		<wp:comment_status><![CDATA[open]]></wp:comment_status>
		<wp:ping_status><![CDATA[open]]></wp:ping_status>
		<wp:post_name><![CDATA[hill-street-blues]]></wp:post_name>
		<wp:status><![CDATA[publish]]></wp:status>
		<wp:post_parent>0</wp:post_parent>
		<wp:menu_order>0</wp:menu_order>
		<wp:post_type><![CDATA[post]]></wp:post_type>
		<wp:post_password><![CDATA[]]></wp:post_password>
		<wp:is_sticky>0</wp:is_sticky>
		<category domain="post_tag" nicename="childhoodfamily"><![CDATA[childhood/family]]></category>
		<category domain="post_tag" nicename="imagery"><![CDATA[imagery]]></category>
		<category domain="category" nicename="issue-29-january-2009"><![CDATA[Issue 29 / January 2009]]></category>
		<category domain="post_tag" nicename="memoir"><![CDATA[Memoir]]></category>
		<category domain="category" nicename="nonfiction"><![CDATA[Nonfiction]]></category>
		<category domain="post_tag" nicename="parenting"><![CDATA[parenting]]></category>
		<category domain="post_tag" nicename="plotstructure"><![CDATA[plot/structure]]></category>
		<category domain="post_tag" nicename="speculation"><![CDATA[speculation]]></category>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key><![CDATA[_edit_last]]></wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[2]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key><![CDATA[Author]]></wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[BRYAN FRY]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
	</item>
	<item>
		<title>Review of  Ayaan Hirsi Ali’s Infidel</title>
		<link>http://brevitymag.com/book-reviews/review-of-ayaan-hirsi-alis-infidel/</link>
		<pubDate>Thu, 08 Jan 2009 10:59:10 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[elhajj]]></dc:creator>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://brevitymag.com/?p=4476</guid>
		<description></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[Free Press, 2008

I’m sitting at my desk, sipping from a water bottle with the name of my alma mater scrawled down the side. I might get a cheeseburger for lunch because sometimes I crave greasy foods, and at those times, I don’t care how bad it is for me. I will eat a salad tomorrow and feel better.<a href="http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/0743289692?ie=UTF8&amp;tag=brevitynonfic-20&amp;linkCode=as2&amp;camp=1789&amp;creative=390957&amp;creativeASIN=0743289692"><img class="alignright wp-image-4478 size-full" src="http://brevitymag.com/wp-content/uploads/2015/09/infidel.jpg" alt="infidel" width="390" height="595" /></a>
<p align="left">Enter the Muslim co-worker. In this month of Ramadan, he has asked several of us in the office to fast with him, to share his experience. I am wary; he may be trying to convert me. Really I am a glutton. If I have to choose between salvation and dinner, I already know what I want for dessert.</p>
<p align="left">The co-worker notices the book in my hands and the author’s picture on the cover. He guesses that she’s from Somalia. He’s right.</p>
<p align="left">Another day, another chapter, Ayaan Hirsi Ali has just witnessed her younger sister's genital mutilation at the hands of their grandmother. Ayaan’s turn would be next. My body recoils as I read her words, and I find myself in the shared office bathroom, leaning on the toilet with both hands.</p>
<p align="left">My co-worker is not a violent man. He agrees that violence in the name of religion is wrong. He believes jihad is a misused word, that it is not a call to violence against infidels but to war against one’s own shortcomings. During Ramadan, he says, you cannot blame evil spirits or anyone else for your bad behavior, and you bear the full responsibility of all of your actions. This is why he prays every day and fasts, to practice self control and to purify himself.</p>
<p align="left">My co-worker refrains from criticizing his fellow Muslims. In fact, he does not even criticize the office atheist. He believes it is not his job to say who is a true follower. He can sense my disgust over the violence done to women in the name of his God, but he ventures only to say that what I’ve read does not represent him and that he believes in treating women and all people with kindness and respect. And after Ramadan, he will take our co-workers and me, an infidel, out to lunch.</p>
<p align="left">---</p>
<p align="left"><strong>Mary Richert</strong> is a 2008 MFA graduate of Goucher College. She writes for <a href="http://guardian.co.uk/commentisfree/america" target="_blank">"Comment Is Free,"</a>a blog for the <em>Guardian</em>. Mary also maintains her own blog,<a href="http://notitles.com" target="_blank"> "No Titles."</a></p>]]></content:encoded>
		<excerpt:encoded><![CDATA[]]></excerpt:encoded>
		<wp:post_id>4476</wp:post_id>
		<wp:post_date><![CDATA[2009-01-08 05:59:10]]></wp:post_date>
		<wp:post_date_gmt><![CDATA[2009-01-08 10:59:10]]></wp:post_date_gmt>
		<wp:comment_status><![CDATA[open]]></wp:comment_status>
		<wp:ping_status><![CDATA[open]]></wp:ping_status>
		<wp:post_name><![CDATA[review-of-ayaan-hirsi-alis-infidel]]></wp:post_name>
		<wp:status><![CDATA[publish]]></wp:status>
		<wp:post_parent>0</wp:post_parent>
		<wp:menu_order>0</wp:menu_order>
		<wp:post_type><![CDATA[post]]></wp:post_type>
		<wp:post_password><![CDATA[]]></wp:post_password>
		<wp:is_sticky>0</wp:is_sticky>
		<category domain="category" nicename="book-reviews"><![CDATA[Book Review]]></category>
		<category domain="category" nicename="issue-29-january-2009"><![CDATA[Issue 29 / January 2009]]></category>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key><![CDATA[_edit_last]]></wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[2]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key><![CDATA[Author]]></wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[MARY RICHERT]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
	</item>
	<item>
		<title>Review of  Richard Todd&#039;s The Thing Itself: On the Search for Authenticity</title>
		<link>http://brevitymag.com/book-reviews/review-of-richard-todds-the-thing-itself-on-the-search-for-authenticity/</link>
		<pubDate>Thu, 08 Jan 2009 10:59:09 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[elhajj]]></dc:creator>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://brevitymag.com/?p=4482</guid>
		<description></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[<span style="font-family: Georgia, 'Times New Roman', Times, serif; font-size: medium;">Riverhead, 2008</span>

I’m haunted by past sins and follies: my quip that hurt a friend; the foolish act trying to impress a woman; my silence when my father, being thrown out by my mother, told me he loved me. How we leak guilt and shame. Dear God, forgive us our trespasses. Yet isn’t anyone worth knowing aware he’s let himself down?<a href="http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/1594488517?ie=UTF8&amp;tag=brevitynonfic-20&amp;linkCode=as2&amp;camp=1789&amp;creative=390957&amp;creativeASIN=1594488517"><img class="alignright size-full wp-image-4479" src="http://brevitymag.com/wp-content/uploads/2015/09/thing.jpg" alt="thing" width="179" height="280" /></a>
<p align="left"><em>The Thing Itself: On the Search for Authenticity </em>meditates upon how we feel at this edgy moment about ourselves in our diminished nation. There’s much to lament with so much shorn of context and community. Consider Richard Todd’s local mall—the same as yours or mine: a farmer sold out for profit; a developer bulldozed woods and fields for gain; the mall’s cash registers hum; and we stampede there in welcome postmodern anonymity. “Yet something unfortunate has happened here,” writes Todd. “You can feel it. As you drive past, the scene is not uplifting. No one has been exploited, but everyone has. This is the feeling, of course, that exudes from much of built America, from our endless date-raped landscapes. Something that began as consensual has ended in tears.”</p>
<p align="left">Such malaise wouldn’t be important, except it is. Reading <em>The Thing Itself</em>, I’m reminded how intrinsic emotion is to the matrix we use to gauge what’s worthy—ideas, eateries, politicians, potential mates, house painters. Todd draws on thinkers and poets who’ve grappled with why things don’t feel so good, and he rambles into America in search of its soul. A former executive editor of <em>The Atlantic Monthly</em>, Todd’s poignant scenes arise as if unbidden, the way memories do. At Disney World, he stumbles into a “character breakfast” and Chip, a walking stuffed animal, mauls his dignity. In a Las Vegas bar, Todd watches geysers choreographed to Appalachian Spring, the spectacle an oddly pleasant sacrilege. At colonial theme parks, he fixates upon docents of a certain age wearing mobcaps. Even curmudgeonly Todd finds these things harmless in a certain mood, but they can strike a pang to the heart: here’s the sad residue of authenticity that’s dead and gone.</p>
<p align="left">Despite its probing of our roiled psyches and diminished situation, <em>The Thing Itself</em> left me soberly cheered. We’re a clever species that craves a solid self; we’re successful but yearn to be good. And Todd’s inner life (his thoughts, his tears, his prayers) stirred me, suggesting how I might grow. Nurture spirit. Read and think. Keep a cold eye on society but see what’s holy.</p>
<p align="left">“Most people can’t be saints, and most objects can’t be art,” Todd whispers, “but in each case the extent to which they are marked by the impulse toward grace is a measure of their worth.”</p>
<p align="left">---</p>
<p align="left"><strong>Richard Gilbert</strong> earned an MFA in Goucher College’s creative nonfiction program in 2007, where he knew Richard Todd. Gilbert’s work has appeared in <em>Orion, SNReview</em>, and <em>Farming: People, Land, and Community. </em>He teaches at Ohio University and is working on a memoir. He maintains <a href="http://richardgilbert.wordpress.com/" target="_blank">NARRATIVE</a>, a blog on narrative nonfiction writing and teaching.</p>]]></content:encoded>
		<excerpt:encoded><![CDATA[]]></excerpt:encoded>
		<wp:post_id>4482</wp:post_id>
		<wp:post_date><![CDATA[2009-01-08 05:59:09]]></wp:post_date>
		<wp:post_date_gmt><![CDATA[2009-01-08 10:59:09]]></wp:post_date_gmt>
		<wp:comment_status><![CDATA[open]]></wp:comment_status>
		<wp:ping_status><![CDATA[open]]></wp:ping_status>
		<wp:post_name><![CDATA[review-of-richard-todds-the-thing-itself-on-the-search-for-authenticity]]></wp:post_name>
		<wp:status><![CDATA[publish]]></wp:status>
		<wp:post_parent>0</wp:post_parent>
		<wp:menu_order>0</wp:menu_order>
		<wp:post_type><![CDATA[post]]></wp:post_type>
		<wp:post_password><![CDATA[]]></wp:post_password>
		<wp:is_sticky>0</wp:is_sticky>
		<category domain="category" nicename="book-reviews"><![CDATA[Book Review]]></category>
		<category domain="category" nicename="issue-29-january-2009"><![CDATA[Issue 29 / January 2009]]></category>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key><![CDATA[_edit_last]]></wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[2]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key><![CDATA[Author]]></wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[RICHARD GILBERT]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
	</item>
	<item>
		<title>Review of  Kim Sunée’s Trail of Crumbs: Hunger, Love, and the Search for Home</title>
		<link>http://brevitymag.com/book-reviews/review-of-kim-sunees-trail-of-crumbs-hunger-love-and-the-search-for-home/</link>
		<pubDate>Thu, 08 Jan 2009 10:59:05 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[elhajj]]></dc:creator>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://brevitymag.com/?p=4484</guid>
		<description></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[<span style="font-family: Georgia, 'Times New Roman', Times, serif; font-size: medium;">Grand Central Publishing, 2008</span>
<p align="left">“I leaned back and closed my eyes, ready for him to kiss me, but he filled my mouth with sweetness I had never known before, deeper than honey. I opened my eyes to a handful of fresh fat figs dripping with their own milk.”<a href="http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/0446697907?ie=UTF8&amp;tag=brevitynonfic-20&amp;linkCode=as2&amp;camp=1789&amp;creative=390957&amp;creativeASIN=0446697907"><img class="alignright size-full wp-image-4477" src="http://brevitymag.com/wp-content/uploads/2015/09/crumbs.jpg" alt="crumbs" width="185" height="275" /></a></p>
<p align="left">Kim Sunée’s memoir is a fairy tale where eating and romance feed off each other. Abandoned at age three in a crowded Korean marketplace, adopted by a family in New Orleans, a place she never feels at home, except for her Poppy’s Creole kitchen, she flees to Europe during college. At twenty-two, she falls in love with a famous French industrialist, who whisks her off to live a luxurious lifestyle highlighted by entertaining and travel. Sunée’s passion for cooking allows her to slide into her role as high priestess of her lover’s kitchen in Provence, where she delights and seduces him, as well as their many guests.</p>
<p align="left">On one occasion, Sunée serves an elaborate meal of melon soup, ratatouille-stuffed cabbage leaves, duck breast with raspberry-balsamic reduction, fromage blanc sorbet with candied ginger….</p>
<p align="left">As I read, I yearn for the food, the companionship of the table, and the scents of lavender and thyme, the perfume of Provence. Yet here I am, alone in a woodsy New York suburb. My husband moved out ten months ago. Our two young children are with him for the week.</p>
<p align="left">The subject of food has always compelled me, which is why I picked up <em>Trail of Crumbs</em>, to quell a gnawing hunger I can never fill. My ex tells me it’s because I am a depressive who can’t be satisfied except for brief highs, such as a good meal.</p>
<p align="left">I relate to Sunée, who says of her French lover, “I want Olivier to love me until there’s nothing left. I want him to fill me whole, to drink me up until I disappear, until I am no longer discernible as a race or a gender, but just simply an empty shape that needs defining, filling in.”</p>
<p align="left">I crave this level of intimacy. But Sunée becomes overpowered by Olivier, who often says, "<i>Je veux tout t’offir</i>" (I want to give you everything.) She leaves him to make her way back to herself. It’s a lesson in existential loneliness—even in love we are alone.</p>
<p align="left">Tonight in the kitchen I want to channel Sunée and decide on ratatouille. It is August—eggplant, tomatoes, and zucchini are in abundance. Alone at the table, I tuck into the silky braise of vegetables, experiencing a serenity only good food can bring. This gratification may be fleeting, but at least I know it can be recaptured again and again with the right ingredients.</p>
<p align="left">---</p>
<p align="left"><strong>Stephanie Susnjara</strong> is a freelance writer and editor based in Katonah, New York. Her essays have appeared in the anthologies <a href="http://www.amazon.com/exec/obidos/ASIN/1580050921/ref=nosim/brevitynonfic-20" target="_blank">Women Who Eat: A New Generation on the Glory of Food</a>(Seal Press/2003) and <a href="http://www.amazon.com/exec/obidos/ASIN/1590512421/ref=nosim/brevitynonfic-20" target="_blank">Our Roots are Deep with Passion: Creative Nonfiction Collects Essays by Italian American Writers</a> (Other Press/2005), as well as other publications. She received her MFA in creative nonfiction from Goucher College in 2000 and frequently writes about food.</p>]]></content:encoded>
		<excerpt:encoded><![CDATA[]]></excerpt:encoded>
		<wp:post_id>4484</wp:post_id>
		<wp:post_date><![CDATA[2009-01-08 05:59:05]]></wp:post_date>
		<wp:post_date_gmt><![CDATA[2009-01-08 10:59:05]]></wp:post_date_gmt>
		<wp:comment_status><![CDATA[open]]></wp:comment_status>
		<wp:ping_status><![CDATA[open]]></wp:ping_status>
		<wp:post_name><![CDATA[review-of-kim-sunees-trail-of-crumbs-hunger-love-and-the-search-for-home]]></wp:post_name>
		<wp:status><![CDATA[publish]]></wp:status>
		<wp:post_parent>0</wp:post_parent>
		<wp:menu_order>0</wp:menu_order>
		<wp:post_type><![CDATA[post]]></wp:post_type>
		<wp:post_password><![CDATA[]]></wp:post_password>
		<wp:is_sticky>0</wp:is_sticky>
		<category domain="category" nicename="book-reviews"><![CDATA[Book Review]]></category>
		<category domain="category" nicename="issue-29-january-2009"><![CDATA[Issue 29 / January 2009]]></category>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key><![CDATA[_edit_last]]></wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[2]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key><![CDATA[Author]]></wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[STEPHANIE SUSNJARA]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
	</item>
	<item>
		<title>“Perhapsing”: The Use of Speculation in Creative Nonfiction</title>
		<link>http://brevitymag.com/craft-essays/perhapsing-the-use-of-speculation-in-creative-nonfiction/</link>
		<pubDate>Thu, 08 Jan 2009 10:59:03 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[elhajj]]></dc:creator>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://brevitymag.com/?p=4486</guid>
		<description></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[At some point, writers of creative nonfiction come to a road block or dead end in our writing, where we don’t have access to the facts we need to tell our story or to sustain our reflection with depth and fullness. If only it was ethical to just make something up, we might think, or to elaborate a bit on what we know. But of course, then we wouldn’t be writing creative nonfiction. It might appear that our choices in such cases are to either abandon the topic or write a thinly developed scene or reflection.

In <em>Woman Warrior</em>, Maxine Hong Kingston offers another option. In the first essay, “No Name Woman,” Kingston’s mother tells her a brief, cautionary tale about her father’s sister in China, who became pregnant even though her husband had been away for years. On the night the baby is born, villagers raid the family’s house and farm. The aunt gives birth in a pigsty, and then kills herself and her baby by jumping into the well from which the family drank. Kingston’s father was so shamed by his sister’s behavior that Kingston was forbidden to ever mention her in his presence.

In order to write the essay, Kingston needed a deeper, fuller understanding of her aunt’s life and a clearer picture of what happened the night she drowned. Since the only information Kingston had was the bare-bones story that her mother had told her, Kingston chose to speculate an interior life for her aunt. I call this technique “perhapsing.” Notice in the following passage how Kingston uses perhapsing to imagine an identity for the man who impregnated her aunt (italics are mine):
<blockquote><em>Perhaps</em> she had encountered him in the fields or on the mountain where the daughters-in-law collected fuel. Or <em>perhaps</em> he first noticed her in the marketplace. He was not a stranger because the village housed no strangers. She had to have dealings with him other than sex. <em>Perhaps</em> he worked in an adjoining field, or he sold her the cloth for the dress she sewed and wore. His demand must have surprised, then terrified her. She obeyed him; she always did as she was told.</blockquote>
The word <em>perhaps</em> cues the reader that the information Kingston is imparting is not factual but speculative. Kingston doesn’t need to use <em>perhaps</em> in every sentence, because we can see that one perhapsing leads to another. We can also see that when Kingston presents facts (“He was not a stranger because the village housed no strangers. She had to have dealings with him other than sex”), she does not begin those sentences with <em>perhaps</em>.

Elsewhere in the essay, Kingston uses other words and phrases to alert the reader when she’s moving from fact to conjecture (italics are mine):
<blockquote>“<em>It could very well have been</em>, however, that my aunt did not take subtle enjoyment of her friend, but, a wild woman, kept rollicking company. Imagining her free with sex doesn’t fit, though.”

She <em>may have been</em> unusually beloved, the precious only daughter, spoiled and mirror gazing because of the affection the family lavished on her.</blockquote>
By perhapsing, Kingston offers motives, actions, justifications, and specific details that add richness, texture, and complexity absent in her mother’s account, without crossing the line into fiction. Kingston believed that by remaining silent about her desperate and defiant ancestor, she was participating in her aunt’s punishment. By perhapsing, Kingston freed both herself and her aunt from the traditions that bound them.

Perhapsing can be particularly useful when writing about childhood memories, which are often incomplete because of a child’s limited understanding at the time of the event, and the loss of details and clarity due to the passage of time.

Susan Griffin offers a fine example of how perhapsing allows a writer to bring detail and understanding to a memory of a long-ago event. In “Red Shoes,” an essay in her collection <em>The Eros of Everyday Life</em>, Griffin recounts a childhood memory in which her grandmother gave her a pair of red shoes that she coveted. This memory is essential to the essay because it serves as the springboard and touchstone for Griffin’s musings on such dichotomies as mind versus body, domestic versus private spheres, public versus private memories, and genre (fiction versus nonfiction; detached, intellectualized essay versus intimate memoir). In the following segment, notice the various ways in which Griffin signals her uncertainty as she presents her memory of being given the red shoes – if, indeed, she was given the shoes (italics and ellipses are mine):
<blockquote>I was, <em>I suppose</em>, shopping with my grandmother in the department store with the X-ray machine that made a green picture of the bones in my feet. I have the vague feeling my grandmother finds red impractical. . . . <em>I cannot remember</em> whether or not my grandmother let me have those shoes. . . .<em> Perhaps</em> she did buy me those red shoes. I can see them now in my closet which was also her second closet, the closet of the black silk robe, the place where she kept her rarer treasures, her two fur coats, worn only on the most special occasions. . . . and, <em>am I embellishing here</em>, her sweater with the rhinestones on it, or were they pearls?</blockquote>
When an author’s memories of concrete details are sketchy or absent, the technique of perhapsing not only allows her to recreate the scene effectively, it also helps establish her as a reliable narrator. Because Griffin admits what she doesn’t know and tells me when she’s speculating, I trust her to be a reliable narrator and follow her willingly through her other memories and complex, philosophical wanderings.

<hr />

<strong>Writing Exercise</strong>:

Select a passage in one of your essays that could be made richer and fuller through the use of speculation. If your memory of the time you learned a family secret is fuzzy and incomplete, “perhaps” details and plausible dialogue. If the person you’re profiling can’t or won’t say why he began playing the banjo when his wife left him, “perhaps” some likely motives. If you and your family don’t know why your grandmother inserted such a peculiar clause into her will, “perhaps” plausible motives. In addition to <em>perhaps</em>, other words and phrases you can use include<em> maybe, suppose, if, what if, might have/could have, possibly, imagine, wonder, perchance.</em>

---

<strong>Lisa Knopp</strong> is the author of four collections of essays: <em><a href="http://www.amazon.com/exec/obidos/ASIN/0803211430/ref=nosim/brevitynonfic-20" target="_blank">Interior Places</a></em> (2008) and <em><a href="http://www.amazon.com/exec/obidos/ASIN/0803278144/ref=nosim/brevitynonfic-20" target="_blank">The Nature of Home</a></em> (2002), published by University of Nebraska Press, and <em>Flight Dreams: A Life in the Midwestern Landscape</em> (1998) and <em>Field of Vision</em> (1996), published by the University of Iowa Press. Knopp is currently working on a collection of essays, <em>Three Rivers</em>, about the Mississippi, Missouri and Platte rivers. Her essays have appeared in literary quarterlies including <em>Missouri Review</em>, <em>Michigan Review</em>, <em>Gettysburg Review</em>, <em>Northwest Review</em>, <em>Cream City Review</em>, <em>South Dakota Review</em>, <em>Connecticut Review</em>, <em>Shenandoah</em>, <em>Creative Nonfiction</em>, <em>ISLE,</em> and <em>Cimarron Review</em>. Five of her essays have been listed as notable essays in <em>Best American Essays</em> (2008, 2002, 2001, 1994, and 1990). Knopp is an associate professor of English at the University of Nebraska-Omaha and a visiting faculty member in Goucher College’s low-residency MFA in Creative Nonfiction program in Baltimore.

&nbsp;]]></content:encoded>
		<excerpt:encoded><![CDATA[]]></excerpt:encoded>
		<wp:post_id>4486</wp:post_id>
		<wp:post_date><![CDATA[2009-01-08 05:59:03]]></wp:post_date>
		<wp:post_date_gmt><![CDATA[2009-01-08 10:59:03]]></wp:post_date_gmt>
		<wp:comment_status><![CDATA[open]]></wp:comment_status>
		<wp:ping_status><![CDATA[open]]></wp:ping_status>
		<wp:post_name><![CDATA[perhapsing-the-use-of-speculation-in-creative-nonfiction]]></wp:post_name>
		<wp:status><![CDATA[publish]]></wp:status>
		<wp:post_parent>0</wp:post_parent>
		<wp:menu_order>0</wp:menu_order>
		<wp:post_type><![CDATA[post]]></wp:post_type>
		<wp:post_password><![CDATA[]]></wp:post_password>
		<wp:is_sticky>0</wp:is_sticky>
		<category domain="category" nicename="craft-essays"><![CDATA[Craft Essay]]></category>
		<category domain="category" nicename="issue-29-january-2009"><![CDATA[Issue 29 / January 2009]]></category>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key><![CDATA[_edit_last]]></wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[2]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key><![CDATA[Author]]></wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[LISA KNOPP]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
	</item>
	<item>
		<title>On Practice: Letter to Holly from Cougar Ridge</title>
		<link>http://brevitymag.com/craft-essays/on-practice-letter-to-holly-from-cougar-ridge/</link>
		<pubDate>Thu, 08 Jan 2009 10:59:01 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[elhajj]]></dc:creator>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://brevitymag.com/?p=4488</guid>
		<description></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[Editor's note: Brenda Miller and Holly Hughes are collaborating on a book on writing tentatively titled <em>The Pen and the Bell: Reading, Writing, and the Contemplative Life</em>, which will feature a series of letters the authors have written to each other. Following is a sneak peek at a letter by Miller that speaks to the practice of letter writing as a form of contemplative practice, and to the concept of “practice” in general. (Keep an eye out for writing exercises and suggested readings at the conclusion.)

<hr />

October 14, 2008
Letter to Holly from Cougar Ridge

Dear Holly,

Your letter from Hornsby Island arrived just as I’ve begun my own mini writing retreat in Port Townsend. I write this to you in a cozy studio apartment in the trees, my dog asleep in her tiny bed. The gas fireplace flickers and pops. Morning sun parts the clouds from the storm the night before.

I think about your apples that washed onshore and the gifts the world offers us when we slow down long enough to notice. And I’ve been thinking about letter writing as its own form of contemplative practice – a way of slowing down, getting into the present, honing our senses so that we can express a moment fully and then offer that moment to the other as a gift. Something shifts when we feel ourselves not as solitary beings, existing in our solitary ways, but in deep communion with another. Our writing takes on a new kind of vitality when it spins outward in this way; having a “you” as a counterpoint to the all-too-familiar “I” provides an audience that helps shape our thoughts.

Letter writing, as many have noted, is a dying art. We now have so many ways of instantaneous communication (to the point of absurdity), and so we communicate constantly, back and forth, the world becoming an endless stream of trivial matters that take up all our attention. To sit down to write a real letter, ideally with pen in hand, requires at least a few moments of “stopping,” becoming present both to where we are and to the distant correspondent. I love the word “correspondent.” It implies that the two of you work together in responding to the world, you are “co-responding.” And it’s just the two of you, for a moment, cordoned off from the busy-ness that swirls around outside. In a world where we can now overhear – whether we want to or not – the most intimate conversations as people blather on their cell phones, this moment of true intimate communication is a rare gift indeed.

I think of the letters of Emily Dickinson, or John Keats, or Elizabeth Bishop, or Rainier Maria Rilke. I think of the heart-stopping letter-poems of Richard Hugo, where we are allowed to witness two minds – two hearts – moving together. Here’s a little bit from Hugo’s “Letter to Kathy from Wisdom”:
<blockquote>….Oh, my tenderest
raccoon, odd animal from nowhere scratching for a home,
please believe I want to plant whatever poem will grow
inside you like a decent life. And when the wheat you’ve known
forever sours in the wrong wind and you smell it
dying in those acres where you played, please know
old towns we loved in matter, lovers matter, playmates, toys,
and we take from our lives those days when everything moved,
tree, cloud, water, sun, blue between two clouds, and moon,
days that danced, vibrating days, chance poem. I want one
who’s wondrous and kind to you. I want him sensitive
to wheat and how wheat bends in cloud shade without wind.
Kathy, this is the worst time of day, nearing five, gloom
ubiquitous as harm, work shifts changing. And our lives
are on the line. Until we die our lives are on the mend.</blockquote>
Hugo’s letter-poems have a depth of emotion, a surging momentum, an authenticity to them that I think might be impossible to achieve without both the correspondent and the place from which this correspondence is born. Each of his poems is titled like this, “Letter to ______ from _______,” the poet knowing that both the correspondent and the place are the foundations for these pieces that feel not so much like poems, but urgent communications. In this particular missive, the poet offers the gift of his attention, not only to Kathy’s sorrow, but to the land that is her home, the land that shapes her. All these things “matter,” including the small things the casual observer might not notice, such as the way “wheat bends in cloud shade without wind.” The litany of physical details leads us inexorably to the emotional heart of the poem, a proclamation not only to Kathy but to the poet, and to us: “Until we die our lives are on the mend.” We’ve arrived at this place together – our common humanity – line by line, moment by moment, through the force of the poet’s attention.

One of my favorite lines from a Dickinson letter goes something like this: “The world weaves a spell so exquisite that everything conspires to break it.” It’s our task as contemplative writers to keep weaving that spell. To incant the magic of the world, lure it out of its hiding place. To hold ourselves and our readers spellbound. Letter writing can be its own contemplative practice, creating a quiet, vibrant space for a communication that speaks from the core of the self.  Tolstoy once said that great art speaks “from soul to soul,” and we can revive letter writing as a practice of this soulful murmuring.

You speak of serendipity – its own form of magic. I had a serendipitous moment the other day: on the radio show “To the Best of Our Knowledge,” guitarist Glenn Kurtz talked about the beautiful art of practicing. He said: “My attention alone makes this a performance. Attention changes everything…each instant is urgent. Practice lets us grow in our own time. Every single day you fail; practice is the process of returning, trying again. Practice is the inward turn that allows us to move forward. Practice is a dream of perfection.” His words made me think in new ways about how both writing and contemplation are forms of practice in this elemental way: practicing the way one might practice the guitar, attuning ourselves to our instruments.

As a kid, I envied the other children who had something to practice: violin, piano, basketball, gymnastics. Though most of them claimed to hate it and slunk to their practices with pouts and glares, they still seemed to have a sense of purpose about them, carrying their sturdy black cases, or changing into their uniforms. I had nothing, no special way of delineating the day. It’s not my parents’ fault; I probably adamantly refused all lessons to the point of hysteria, afraid of failure, and so I wandered rather aimlessly in my backyard, pretending to practice. Like Snoopy, I became “world famous”: the world-famous gymnast practicing her round off from the jungle gym; the world-famous basketball star, clumsily dribbling my brother’s basketball on the makeshift court and heaving the ball toward the net. I swam in the pool, around and around, pretending to practice synchronized swimming with an invisible team.

What did I yearn for so much as I did my solitary, imaginary practices in the backyard? I think it was the sense of growing better at something, a visible, tangible manifestation of growth. I wanted to be shaped by practice, to have some kind of skill infiltrating my very being. I wanted the focus and direction practice gave to the amorphous days. And I wanted to feel a part of something – either part of a team that grew better together, or a servant to something beautiful, like music. When I went away to college, I would see the serious musicians in their practice rooms, the little windows in the doors allowing a glimpse of their bodies leaning into the music. They stayed in there for hours at a time. There seemed something almost monkish about them, in their devotion, and they emerged weary, sometimes frustrated, but triumphant. They could put away their violins or cellos for the day, knowing they had spent the day well.

Kim Stafford has likened the practice of writing to the practice of playing the violin; he writes about how a violin, played every day, will keep the vibrations of the music in its body, even while lying still and silent on the wall. If it is not played every day, the vibrations dissipate and the wood grows lifeless. Our own writing practice can infuse our bodies with the energy and vibrancy of music, keeping us always at the ready to unleash a gorgeous song. I’ve mentioned before that “discipline” is an extension of the word “disciple,” and if we consider ourselves disciples of writing, we might find the energy and devotion we need to keep going, even when it feels like the practice is arduous. Practice, as Glenn Kurtz said, “is the process of returning, trying again.”

As an adult, I have many things I practice: writing, meditation, cooking, yoga, knitting, bread-making, friendship. We can reclaim the word, as Kurtz has, and see practice, itself, as the point. We are always practicing, until the very end. For a while there was a popular bumper sticker: “Life is not a dress rehearsal,” it commanded, but now I want to say back to it, “Well, golly, maybe life is a dress rehearsal, maybe there is no one perfect performance toward which we’re aiming.” We just keep practicing, over and over. When we meditate, and when we write, we are practicing every day, our arms and minds and hearts in constant motion, warming up. There’s something kind, gentle and forgiving about seeing both contemplation and writing (and life itself) as practice, while at the same time, there’s something quite rigorous about it. As a kid, I even fantasized about the mean coach or music teacher who would make me practice for hours on end – an authority figure who might yell at me, but who would eventually melt that stern facade and beam with pride at my progress. We all need that coach, whether it be kind or curmudgeonly, strict or nurturing. We need something urging us on.

There’s a joke I told all the time as a kid: A tourist in New York stops a man carrying a violin case to ask for directions. “How do you get to Carnegie Hall?” she asks, holding out her crumpled map. The musician replies,“Practice, practice, practice.”

Practice, practice, practice. It’s all we can ever do.

Yours truly,
Brenda

<hr />

Suggested Readings:

<a href="http://www.amazon.com/exec/obidos/ASIN/0674250702/ref=nosim/brevitynonfic-20" target="_blank">The Letters of Emily Dickinson</a>
Richard Hugo,<a href="http://www.amazon.com/exec/obidos/ASIN/0393044904/ref=nosim/brevitynonfic-20" target="_blank"> <em>31 Letters and 13 Dreams</em></a>
Rainier Maria Rilke, <em><a href="http://www.amazon.com/exec/obidos/ASIN/0486422453/ref=nosim/brevitynonfic-20" target="_blank">Letters to a Young Poet</a></em>
Kim Stafford,“Playing Daily, Playing in Tune,” <em>from <a href="http://www.amazon.com/exec/obidos/ASIN/0820324965/ref=nosim/brevitynonfic-20" target="_blank">The Muses Among Us: Eloquent Listening and Other Pleasures of the Writer’s Craf</a>t
</em>Glenn Kurtz, <em><a href="http://www.amazon.com/exec/obidos/ASIN/0307278751/ref=nosim/brevitynonfic-20" target="_blank">Practicing:</a></em> <a href="http://www.amazon.com/exec/obidos/ASIN/0307278751/ref=nosim/brevitynonfic-20"><em>A Musician’s Return to Music</em></a>

<hr />

<strong>Suggested Writing Exercises</strong>

1. Make it a habit to write a letter at least once a week. This can be a letter you send or one you keep for yourself alone. Your correspondent can remain the same, or you can switch it up from week to week. Your correspondent can be human or animal or spirit. Take a few moments to stop and breathe before beginning. Write each letter for at least a half hour, communicating whatever is most “present” for you at the time. Save these letters and see what you might be able to mine for other writing.

2. What did you practice as a young person? Write some scenes about something you practiced a lot as a child or a teenager. What was this practice like? Who was your coach or teacher? What kind of discipline did it take? If you stopped practicing, why did you stop? What do you practice now?

---

<a href="http://myweb.facstaff.wwu.edu/millerb" target="_blank"><strong>Brenda Miller</strong></a> is the author of <em><a href="http://www.amazon.com/exec/obidos/ASIN/1889330698/ref=nosim/brevitynonfic-20" target="_blank">Season of the Body</a></em> (Sarabande Books, 2002) and co-author of<em><a href="http://www.amazon.com/exec/obidos/ASIN/0071444947/ref=nosim/brevitynonfic-20" target="_blank">Tell it Slant: Writing and Shaping Creative Nonfiction</a></em> (McGraw-Hill, 2003).  Her newest collection of essays, <em>Blessing of the Animals</em>, is forthcoming from Eastern Washington University Press in January 2009. Her work has received five Pushcart Prizes and has been published in such journals as <em>Fourth Genre</em>, <em>Creative Nonfiction</em>, <em>Brevity</em>, <em>The Sun</em>, <em>Utne Reader</em>, <em>Georgia Review</em> and <em>Witness</em>. Miller is an associate professor of English at Western Washington University and serves as editor-in-chief of the <a href="http://www.wwu.edu/bhreview/" target="_blank">Bellingham Review</a>.

&nbsp;]]></content:encoded>
		<excerpt:encoded><![CDATA[]]></excerpt:encoded>
		<wp:post_id>4488</wp:post_id>
		<wp:post_date><![CDATA[2009-01-08 05:59:01]]></wp:post_date>
		<wp:post_date_gmt><![CDATA[2009-01-08 10:59:01]]></wp:post_date_gmt>
		<wp:comment_status><![CDATA[open]]></wp:comment_status>
		<wp:ping_status><![CDATA[open]]></wp:ping_status>
		<wp:post_name><![CDATA[on-practice-letter-to-holly-from-cougar-ridge]]></wp:post_name>
		<wp:status><![CDATA[publish]]></wp:status>
		<wp:post_parent>0</wp:post_parent>
		<wp:menu_order>0</wp:menu_order>
		<wp:post_type><![CDATA[post]]></wp:post_type>
		<wp:post_password><![CDATA[]]></wp:post_password>
		<wp:is_sticky>0</wp:is_sticky>
		<category domain="category" nicename="craft-essays"><![CDATA[Craft Essay]]></category>
		<category domain="category" nicename="issue-29-january-2009"><![CDATA[Issue 29 / January 2009]]></category>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key><![CDATA[_edit_last]]></wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[2]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key><![CDATA[Author]]></wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[BRENDA MILLER]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
	</item>
</channel>
</rss>
