<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:excerpt="http://wordpress.org/export/1.2/excerpt/" xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/" xmlns:wp="http://wordpress.org/export/1.2/"><channel><title>Brevity: A Journal of Concise Literary Nonfiction</title><link>http://brevitymag.com</link><description>Brevity: The journal devoted exclusively to the concise literary nonfiction.</description><pubDate>Fri, 28 Apr 2017 21:01:20 +0000</pubDate><language>en-US</language><wp:wxr_version>1.2</wp:wxr_version><wp:base_site_url>http://brevitymag.com</wp:base_site_url><wp:base_blog_url>http://brevitymag.com</wp:base_blog_url><wp:author><wp:author_id>3</wp:author_id><wp:author_login>elhajj</wp:author_login><wp:author_email>tim.elhajj@gmail.com</wp:author_email><wp:author_display_name>Tim ELhajj</wp:author_display_name><wp:author_first_name>Tim</wp:author_first_name><wp:author_last_name>Elhajj</wp:author_last_name></wp:author><wp:category><wp:term_id>207</wp:term_id><wp:category-nicename>issue-28-2008</wp:category-nicename><wp:category-parent /><wp:cat_name>Issue 28 / Fall 2008</wp:cat_name></wp:category><item><title>Accident</title><link /><pubDate /><dc:creator /><guid isPermaLink="false" /><description /><content:encoded><![CDATA[[<p><a href="http://whos.amung.us/show/9bf9580b"><img alt="web counter" border="0" height="29" src="http://whos.amung.us/widget/9bf9580b" width="81"/></a></p>, <p>\n<strong>By John Calderazzo</strong>\n<img align="right" height="299" hspace="20" src="https://www.creativenonfiction.org/brevity/past%20issues/brev28/pix28/blobos.jpg" vspace="5" width="398"> </img></p>, <p align="left">Not really looking as I crank the engine and start downhill  for town, I tilt my head out my window in a rush of wind to take in winter  stars and sweep away the fumes from a petty argument at home. \xa0My escape  velocity: not fast enough, but faster than I should be going.</p>, <p align="left">Right away I pass a pickup and a jeep parked oddly on the road. \xa0My  headlights wash over a car upturned in a field and people trotting towards it.</p>, <p align="left">I pull over on stiff grass.<br>\n          In a wavering of flashlights: no dents or shattered glass. But hurrying through  mashed down weeds and settling dust, I see the car bottom up, naked in the  glare of strangers and the Milky Way, a flipped turtle, legs flailing. \xa0In  the passenger seat a woman hangs upside-down.</br></p>, <p align="left">She pounds the dash with a fist and wails at the dumbstruck sky, \u201cWhat have you  DONE to me?\u201d<br>\n          She\u2019s unbuckled, lowered, and pulled out, crying. \xa0Then a man crawls from  the driver\u2019s side, his left hand bleeding, his right holding a bottle sloshing  with something clear, vodka or gin. \xa0He stands and slings it into the  dark. \xa0A far off thump.</br></p>, <p align="left">\u201cYou tried to KILL me!\u201d she yells from where she\u2019s sitting now, a jacket heaped  over her, then a child\u2019s comforter.</p>, <p align="left">Hot metal ticks.</p>, <p align="left">I smell dripping gasoline and duck fast to check the back seat. \xa0\u201cIS THERE  ANYONE ELSE?\u201d I call out.</p>, <p align="left">\u201cNO,\u201d she calls back. \xa0\u201cBut  where\u2019s my shoe? \xa0I\u2019m COLD.\u201d</p>, <p align="left">The stunned man is suddenly mumbling at my side, \u201cGotta get that shoe . . . .\u201d  \xa0Then lurching towards the car he tries to light a cigarette.</p>, <p align="left">\u201cHEY DON\u2019T!\u201d I shout and dive away, rolling.</p>, <p align="left">In my mind\u2019s eye: WOOF! \xa0A pillow of orange heat blowing him back.</p>, <p align="left">Soon enough he staggers up and starts to wander in a circle. \xa0\u201cThat shoe .  . . .\u201d</p>, <p align="left">We stand around and watch. \xa0I think about an eyebrow I might no longer  quite feel, the woman\u2019s face shining wet in flickering firelight.</p>, <p align="left">Finally, sirens in the distance.</p>, <p align="left">From just uphill I hear our two  dachshunds, bodies tensed at the backyard fence,<br>\n            snouts lifted straight up, sky howling, as they tend to with coyotes and every  ambulance that sprints out from town. \xa0I imagine my wife coming out to  stand beside them, then looking down at all the lights and thinking, OH JESUS  IT\u2019S HIM.</br></p>, <p align="left">So I take my leave. \xa0Driving home, I tilt my head into cool night air and  wonder if that upturned woman, as she hung briefly in the dark, noticed how  much space there is between the stars and how quietly they burn.</p>, <p aligh="left" align="left"><strong><a href="mailto:John.Calderazzo@colostate.edu">John Calderazzo</a></strong> teaches creative nonfiction  writing at Colorado State University, where he has created and helps direct a  teaching climate change across the university curriculum program. \xa0His  work has been cited in <em>Best American Stories</em> and <em>Best American Essays</em> and has  appeared in many magazines, including <em>Audubon, Georgia Review, Orion</em>, and<em> Witness</em>. \xa0His most recent book is <a href="http://www.amazon.com/exec/obidos/ASIN/1592283896/brevitynonfic-20" target="_blank">Rising Fire: Volcanoes and Our Inner  Lives</a>. \xa0His next will be a book of poetry, <em>At the Night Window</em>.</p>, <p align="center">\xa0</p>, <p align="right"><font size="2">photo by <a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/dinty/" target="_blank">Dinty W. Moore</a></font></p>]]]>None</content:encoded><excerpt:encoded /><wp:post_id /><wp:post_date>2000-01-01 19:20:00</wp:post_date><wp:post_date_gmt /><wp:comment_status>open</wp:comment_status><wp:ping_status>open</wp:ping_status><wp:post_name /><wp:status>draft</wp:status><wp:post_parent>0</wp:post_parent><wp:menu_order>0</wp:menu_order><wp:post_type>post</wp:post_type><wp:post_password /><wp:is_sticky>0</wp:is_sticky><category domain="post_tag" nicename="characterization">characterization</category><wp:postmeta><wp:meta_key>_edit_last</wp:meta_key><wp:meta_value>2</wp:meta_value></wp:postmeta><wp:postmeta><wp:meta_key>Author</wp:meta_key><wp:meta_value>JIM BEAM</wp:meta_value></wp:postmeta></item></channel></rss>